to your calls in the second part of the show.
This evening, it starts with an earthquake.
Bird snakes, airplanes.
You guessed it, folks.
It is the start of our new series on eschatology.
This evening's eschatological marvel is the Antichrist.
Is it Antichrist time again already?
Is he alive right now?
How would we spot the signs?
I don't know about you, but when I'm looking
around for the Antichrist, I was asked for myself,
is Lenny Bruce not afraid?
What do you think, Father?
Is he free?
not afraid. How is the Lenny Bruce meter? He was arrested many times. It's old hat to him.
We're really not afraid of arrest, I'll treat you. I liked that we by happenstance. Of course,
people listening to the recording won't know this, but we had that Armageddon lead in.
I know. Like the first thing when it comes on live, the first thing we heard, and it was Dr.
Edith Humphrey, we just heard, say, one word, Armageddon, and then she continued talking on about
escatology or something like that sounds like yes. Yeah, so I
I have an Armageddon question.
Is it really easier to teach an oil driller to be an astronaut
than to teach an astronaut to run a drill?
I don't know.
I mean, that seems counterintuitive to me.
Seems to be like the astronaut could figure out
how to run the equipment.
Whereas being an astronaut kind of tough.
Yeah.
I mean, you might need to have know something about rocket science.
you
You know, I'm suddenly realizing that well, since we have a series on eschatology, I can
bring this in next time maybe, but I'm suddenly realizing that I did not stock up a bunch
of references to a distant thunder and all those rapture scare movies from the 70s and
80s.
Do you remember those?
Yeah.
Well, the real classics are the Jack Vanity B ones, like Mark of the Beast 2.
Right.
And Mark of the Beast 2, what makes it so great is that Jack Vanity P went meta because part
you
the plot of Mark of the Beast 2 is that the rapture happens and someone finds a copy of
Mark of the Beast 1. Nice. And watch is it figures out what happened. Oh man, I've never
seen it. I have to look to some now. Yes. So Jack Van Impeer appears speaking in a Jack
Van Impeer movie in a Jack Van Impeer movie. That's so wonderfully layered. Yeah. And then
You hear that?
that sound of the background that you know it's an inception.
When I was a kid and still kind of going to Baptist churches,
my family took us to, I can't remember it was some other church
than our own, took us to see one of those,
I think it was a distant thunder not deep in the night,
but there were like several of these,
and these were made by the guy who made the blob,
whose name is escaping me off the top of my head,
but it's not the, yeah, the original blob.
Is there a new?
one. Yeah. Yeah, not to be confused with gelatinous cubes. Yeah. Yeah. And it's scared. I mean,
I'm really scared of the hell out of me. I couldn't I couldn't hardly watch them. But now I'm going to
go watch them again because they're super campy. Yeah. Unfortunately with with orthodox eschatology,
there are fewer easy pranks to pull. It's true. Like waiting till your sister goes to the bathroom
and then like leaving your clothes laid out in the chair.
you were. Oh, she won't get it. My kids wouldn't get that joke if I try to pull it on them.
They would just think anyway. Heard an odd. Yeah. Yeah. Well, all right. The Antichrist.
Who is that guy? Yeah. Who is the? Well, uh, Contra won John Lighten. Uh, he is not an anarchist.
Oh, yeah. I mean, he's kind of lawful evil, right? That's the whole deal is he's lawful evil.
Yeah, yeah, and you know in movies he always has a cool name, right? Like Damien Thorn.
Yeah, you know, in the left behind books is in the left behind books, isn't he Romanian?
Yeah, because I think they're going for a whole Dracula thing. I don't know. Oh nice. They're five.
Nice.
So yeah, but that would make it an easy tip off, right? You just had it like really evil sounding name.
But yeah, so we of course as always are going way back into the long ago time to talk about the anti-Christ.
So the anti-Christ the way it's presented, at least the way most people are probably familiar with it from like movies and TV shows.
Other than Good Omen's, which Good Omen's is, I think, just a documentary about eschatology.
Spoilers, you could just watch Good Omen's or read the book better than watching it read the...
book and not listen to the show. But if you're going to still listen to the show anyway,
the idea of the edict Christ as sort of popularly
presented would, and even the term anti-Christ would sort of firmly make you think,
this is a Christian thing. This is some kind of no-vom. This is...
And there are other things here we'll be taking apart as we go forward in this series, right?
But there are whole series of assumptions that, for example, before Christ's ascension
into heaven, everybody had thought that the Messiah was only going to come once and then
once he came, that would be the end and that's it.
And so when he didn't, it's often presented this way, even though he's sculling.
We'll have more to say about them later.
But scholars will say, oh, well, the apostles were intending,
they firmly believed Christ was going to return
within their lifetimes.
And so then when he didn't, they had to figure out, oh, no,
what do we do?
We need institutional structures.
Low, I will be with you always to the end of the age,
but not actually.
The end of the eighth which is going to be very short.
this time. Right. Right. Super shorting. All the previous ages have been hundreds if not thousands
of years. But this one, 30 years and out. Yeah. So that, of course, is a silly assumption
that we'll be taking apart that more later. But so because of that sort of assumption,
everybody assumes that any detailed element of Christian eschatology, including the Antichrist,
must be something that sort of showed up.
somewhere in the second third century, at the earliest, at the earliest. Some of
those there's may have the impression that this is something that showed up with
dispensationalism or something like in the 18th or 19th century, not so. The idea
of an anti-Messiah, because remember Christos is just the Greek word for Messiah.
The idea of an anti-messiah figure predates.
the birth of our Lord. It goes well back into the centuries before Christ and was a firmly
established idea within Second Temple Judaism where the Messianic Hope also had an adversary
who the Messiah would face and feet in his coming and so my
at least of what that would look like and the idea that that adversary would
represent in some way the demonic opponents of humanity in some way in some
way similar to the way the Messiah represented God.
Yeah, talking about the pre-Christian era. A lot of this is fuzzy. There's different
right? Right. Yeah. I mean, just prophecies about a Messiah. It makes sense that
there's gonna be this.
oppositional figure, also prophesied.
Yeah.
Right. Who sort of sums up humans in
and demonic power to some kind of final,
right? Crystalization of that, who's a missile will face.
So, as you may have heard, technically,
the prefix anti, right, or anti,
does not mean against, right?
it means instead of.
which can and can can can can apply against right.
Can apply opposition, but for example, St. Thomas Sunday,
the orthodox church is called anti-pasta.
Yes.
Often that's not with anti-pasta,
which you know, like if you order anti-pasta,
it's instead of pasta.
Yes.
And I am anti-pasta because you are anti-pasta.
just against pasta.
It's wet bread.
It is wet bread.
And they charge you a lot of money for it.
Olive Garden is a racket.
Anyway, wow.
Calling out Olive Garden.
I'm calling out Olive Garden.
A soup salad and breadsticks.
Okay.
The overpriced pasta is wet bread.
It's a racket.
Is there not a Dutch pasta?
Is that not a thing Dutch pasta?
No.
Grill cheese sandwich, same ingredients.
Taste better.
Anyway.
So, yeah, it technically means instead of, right, not in opposition to.
But right, often opposition or antagonism is being implied, right?
And in this case where we're talking about the Messiah and CR episode of the Messiah where
This is a role, right?
This is an office.
This is to place.
oneself into a role instead of someone else, right, or try to replace someone who is supposed to
have a particular role, that implies antagonism, right? That's where that implied antagonism is.
Yeah, there's a usurpation. Yeah, yeah. So when it comes to the scriptures,
So there's a lot of other, we're going to reference.
some of it. There's a lot of second-temple Jewish literature where you can see elements
of these traditions taking shape. But the place where the concept of the Antichrist or
Antimasiah is most crystallized in the Christian scriptures is not where probably most people
would guess. Probably most people would guess the Book of Revelation.
Yeah, right. That's that book that's all about things that are totally in the future, right?
Yeah.
Hehehe.
We will be talking about the beast and the book of Revelation later tonight, but that's
not the passage where really this stuff is crystallized.
And in the place where it's most crystallized, the term antichrist does not actually occur.
Right?
Yep.
There are other terms that are used to describe this figure, but it is this figure.
So the place where this really gets laid out and broken down is actually in the
second chapter of second Thessalonians by St. Paul.
And this is the other two texts that really speak directly, I mean, substantive texts that
speak directly in the New Testament, the Antichrist, are written by St. John and are written later
than Second Thessalonians.
So this is the first canonical Christian text that talks about the Antichrist.
That's one of the reasons why it's important.
It's important because it's kind of a systematic drawing together of the pre-existing Jewish traditions by St. Paul.
And it seems to be, I mean, we can't prove this, but it seems to be referred back to by St. John.
So, beside the book of Revelation in 2 Thessalonians, the other text that really talks about
the Antichrist, that actually uses that term, is first job.
Yeah, I think so.
for his own son's first epistle. And in that at one point, he says, you have heard
that an antichrist will come. So he's saying this, you know, they've already heard this.
Right. Yes. So referring to something might be this might be from St. Paul, but might
also just be, you know, right, second temple Jewish traditions. But the reason why I think
there's good reason to believe it might be from St. Paul. Is that number one
John doesn't say, you remember I told you this or as I have taught you, right? He just says,
you've heard, meaning implying it's for someone else. And number two, if you think about where
St. John was active in and around Ephesus, in Western Asia Minor, these are churches that were
planted by St. Paul. Right. So I think there's good reason to believe that the teaching St. John is
is referring back to his St. Paul's teaching.
how likely it is that any of those churches had the text of 2 Thessalonians is open to question.
Yeah. Right. We're talking about very early, right? But it's not impossible that they did, and even
if they didn't have access to the text, of course, if they had St. Paul saying the same thing directly
to them, right? They're receiving the same tradition, the same teaching that we find recorded in writing
in 2nd Thessalonians 2.
So it's reasonable to believe that St. John is referring to what is outlined by St. Paul and Second
Thessalonians.
So as with First Thessalonians and Second Thessalonians, one of the major themes that St. Paul is after
is, quote unquote, second coming or return.
uses language here, if his appearing.
The term paracetia is
used that usually gets translated as return. I'm sure I've said this before here on the show. I'm
not super partial to the translation of return for paracet because number one, it's not a great translation,
but number two, it's very misleading because I'm in flies that when Christ ascended, he went away
somewhere and then he's gonna come back. And you know, low I am with you always even to the end of the
right like right before he.
That sense. So they kind of applies. He didn't like depart for parts unknown.
Where the ultimate warrior came from, by the way, anyway.
And then, you know, someday he's going to come back.
So part of the CIA literally means like presence.
So you can say, well, if someone isn't present and they become present,
That's where the return translation comes from.
But the way St. Paul, for example, here in Second Vesalonians 2, uses that interchangeably
with appearing means that the idea is more like appearing.
Right.
The idea is more like, yes, Christ is here, but he is not currently here with us in the
way he was with his apostles before the ascension.
Yeah, sort of manifestation, right? Yeah.
But the time will come when he will appear again and he will be present with us in that way again.
Yeah.
And so in First Thessalonians, St. Paul was really trying just to get at the idea of like,
this is a thing that's going to happen. And people are going to rise from the dead when it happens.
and the
reason for that is we have to remember he's writing these letters to Thessalonica. So this is a
Greek city. The majority of the population of this city is Greeks, meaning their former pagans.
pagans had no concept of a physical resurrection. They thought it was kind of silly and ridiculous.
right? Why would you want to come back in your body? Yeah.
And even in Jewish circles, this was a controversial idea at this time, right?
So the Pharisees very much believed in the bottom of resurrection, but like the Sadducees and some other Jewish sex did not.
So there's that famous episode where St. Paul is in front of a bunch of Jewish leaders in acts.
And so he says he's there because of the resurrection and gets them fighting amongst themselves.
the biological issue, right? But
So the idea that sort of the nascent Christian community that has this converted Jewish
core and then a bunch of Gentiles, this Jewish core, there are a bunch of Gentiles, the idea
that he would have to reinforce the idea of the resurrection and first-essalonian makes
perfect sense.
Right.
Like, no, this is the teaching.
I know some of the Jewish Christians there may not have subscribed to this in the past
Yeah.
And I know you, Pagans are clueless about this for Pagans, but right here it is.
And so in 2 Thessalonians he's sort of digging a little deeper into that beyond just the fact of it,
beyond just the fact of Christ appearing and the resurrection of the dead and the judgment, right.
Now he's going a little deeper and so he's going to talk about this anti-Christ figure.
And so in the first couple verses of chapter two
He sort of calls them back to the topic, right, of Christ's imminent appearing of the Parasia.
And then in verse three, he talks about an event that is going to happen first.
Yeah, so here's how that reads. Let no one deceive you in any way. For that day will not come unless
the rebellion comes first, and the man of lawlessness has revealed the Son of Destruction.
Alright, so...
So there is this thing, all right, that has to come first.
Right.
And the word in Greek is literally a postesia in which we get apostasy.
Yeah.
And so this has been referred to for a long, long time as the great apostasy.
has been identified with a bunch of different things.
I mean, especially like in the Reformation, you get this idea that, especially in the radical
Reformation, you know, sort of the second layer of Reformation, of that the church itself
has fallen away. Like, I remember, I can't remember which one of the radical reformers it was,
but he talked about, you know, the church and all her sacraments and everything sort of
disappearing up into heaven for centuries and being completely gone. And now it's back, you know,
that there was this time that the whole church...
fell away and they rediscovered it.
I mean, that's where that notion comes from,
is that second generation of the reformation.
Yeah.
But even in the less radical reformers,
they tended to treat,
they were facing this problem
where from their perspective,
the church had become corrupt.
Yeah, right.
You know, the Eastern church
was over there doing its thing, right?
But these are Western Europeans.
Yeah.
And at the same time,
there was a lot of Millenarianism going on.
Like a lot of people...
believed with all the wars breaking out in Europe and stuff, that it was the end of the world.
Yeah. Yeah. You know, although that's been it, that's been a constant.
Yeah. The year was thousand, everybody thought it was. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It was,
yes, just the latest in people thinking the world was ending. Yeah. But it's has to be it.
It begs, you know, the whole shot. But yeah. And so even somebody like Martin Luther,
right is gonna look at the world said oh yeah look the whole church is
corrupt. This is the apostasy. Now the man of lawlessness is revealed the
Pope's the Antichrist. Which I'm trying to remember which confession is it
that you it's the Belgian confession. Yeah, the Belgian confession like if you
adhere to it, you have to say that the Pope is the anti-Christ. You sign off on
the fact that the Pope is the Antichrist. Not as they will be quick to
distinguish, not the person, the office. I don't think that's actually better.
So he can be elected as anti-Christ by the college of
Yeah, exactly.
Right.
It's anti-Christ.
Yeah.
So the, that idea, right, that was their sort of mode of interpretation.
And this gets carried over in a lot of different ways by different Protestant groups to this day.
You will have, you get this narrative that hopefully we blew up a lot on our St. Constantine
episode where
you know, Constantine founds the Roman Catholic church, right?
It's 325 at Nicae, you know, and some press.
It's so goofy.
It's amazing how those things still keep going around.
I mean, it burns all the Baptist churches.
At least kind of things, right?
And this really is what it's kind of based on.
Automatically this idea that there's going to be this apostasy right
And later groups that emerge just kind of extend the period of the apostasy.
Right. So it goes from oh hey St. Paul's Gospel was lost and then Martin Luther recovered it
to if you're a Mormon the true religion was lost from the world and Joseph Smith recovered it
in the 19th century, right? Yeah. Which...
of folks who hold to the former view about Luther, they get silly. And it's only
sillier by three centuries. That's all I'll say.
So yeah, just this idea that this is something that has already happened, right?
It's sort of one mode of interpretation of this. The other common mode today would be
that this is something that's going to have a particular event that's going to happen.
in the future. So this is this sort of particular great apostasy, but it's not something that's
just happened here in our lifetime, but it's something that's going to happen. And Luther,
Joseph Smith at all just misidentified it, right. And that view is just that at some point in the
future, most of the church will fall away. And that's sometimes very vague and ambiguous
as to exactly what that means. People will appeal to Christ saying when the
Son of Man comes will he find faith upon the earth, right? Just to say it's
going to dwindle down a lot, right? But St. Paul is going to go on to define a
little more what he means. But if we just look at the word apostasy, right? I know we
now use apostasy to mean uh
someone leaving a religion, right?
Yeah. And there's various shades of what that means within Orthodoxy.
Like, some will say it only applies if someone becomes a non-Christian.
Others will say you're apostatizing or I can never I'm never clear.
I've looked this up whether it's apostatizing or apostatizing could be both.
that you're apostasizing if you simply leave the Orthodox Church.
for some other Christian group. I don't know that there's an official consular definition for it.
But maybe there is. No, I'm writing on it. That is more than there is for heretic.
Yeah. Right. Right. Like, it's a word that's used in a certain way.
So, but opposed to see, yeah, if you look at it as a Greek word,
If you look at its preceding Greek usages before St. Paul, right?
is generally used as a military term.
Yeah, right.
It literally means to stand away from, which doesn't really help.
But what it was used to refer to the stasis is to stand.
Right.
and so it was used to mean a defection or retreat.
Right. Military unit was stationed somewhere, they were supposed to stand somewhere, hold the line,
and either they retreated or they defected to the other side, they left their post.
Right. They left their stand.
And that's going to become very important here as we go forward in this passage and what St.
Post's talking about. In fact, that had a military use. But when you get to the end of
Chapter 2 of Second Pesalonia.
where St. Paul sort of gives his exhortation to the Christians in Thessalonica, he uses
Stikita, which means which is the command, right? It's the imperative of Stossis, telling them to stand.
Yeah, right.
Verse 15, stand firm.
Hold fast.
Right. Don't retreat.
Don't surrender.
Right.
treat, never sorry. And so the fact that he uses both terms here, right, and the passage
shows you again sort of what he has in mind here, right. So, and he's going to develop this
more, but you could already see here in verse three that this retreat or defection, right,
failure to stand is what is going to end up.
revealing the person he's talking about. And in verse three, he calls this person by two
different titles. Yeah, you've got man of lawlessness and son of destruction, which, you know,
both excellent band names. Yeah, yeah, they can open for Theophonic Glory Cloud on the, yeah.
I mean, and like the great thing is they could take one of these titles as the band name
and then the other could be the debut album.
You know, man of lawlessness first album Son of Destruction.
Yeah, the podcast that launched 15 metal bands.
I don't think we can launch a thousand, but maybe.
Was this the show that launched a thousand bands?
That are sites medium.
That's the first time I got to quote Marlow on this show
or reference him anyway.
Sorry.
I assume he's promised not to fill him.
No no
Christopher Marlow, Christopher Marlow, the playwright who's a, yeah, that line was this
the face that launched a thousand ships. That's from Fouses by Marlow. Yeah, referring to Helen
of Troy. Yeah. Yeah. Sorry. If you found a way to reference Philip Marlow on this podcast,
that would be way more impressed. Oh, well, that's not a reference I normally would make.
Because that's a tricky one. I know I set these goals for myself, like making all those public
Look at him, he raps.
a couple episodes ago, harder than you think.
So now it's going to be you fill it more or little time.
Anyway, so the first of those titles is the man of lawlessness,
who is sort of revealed by this retreat, the surrender,
this apostasy that happens.
And so the man of lawlessness, right, he's clearly,
St. Paul's clearly identifying a person.
Right. He's got an article there. Right. Um, so this isn't, uh, just a just a just a general
type. So this is referring to a particular person who will be revealed, eschatologically,
but it's not just that one person either. And we could, um, that, that's going to become
plane as we go on in the chapter but it's
already kind of plain in the language St. Paul uses here in verse 3. So first of all the word
he uses for man and yes we're going into this level of excruciating detail. If you listen to my
other podcast you should be used to it by now. The term that he uses for man here is on Thropos.
So for those not...
super familiar with Greek. There are two words that get translated as man. One of them is
on near, which means a man or also mean a husband. Yeah, I mean it's very literally a male person.
Male human. Yeah, right. And then there's Anthropos, which means man in sort of a broader sense.
And the way we used to say man or mankind, which is now known.
longer politically correct. You could say humankind. We can still say that.
No, we have to say humankind and humankind then.
But so I held back a whole bunch of old English right then. You should be very proud of me.
These zoomers.
Anyway, no.
But it's anthropos.
It's man.
It's human in that.
sort of broader sense. Yeah, right. And so but it's not always just used to mean humanity.
It's an interesting word in that regard and there's not a good
there's not really a good easy one word way to make this distinction in English.
Yeah, I mean it really kind of follows the you know the
slightly more archaic usage of man as in, you know, at the dawn of man. So there's ambiguity
there in English just as there is with anthropos. Yeah. Yeah. And by the way, you have the same
thing in Hebrew. You have Atama and Ish. Yeah. And both of those are used, for example,
of Adam in Genesis.
You know, I mean, see his name is one of them, right?
Right.
And he came from the ground.
And the, and Eish, he's also referred to as his name.
And he says, and Eish's name is not even till after.
Fall before that, it's woman, which is Isha, Isha.
Woman.
Yeah.
Yes.
So I was super excited that a 4K Blu-ray of that movie.
is coming out and that I saw that it was the 30th anniversary edition and my
bones turned to powder. Oh no. And I started to decay. I know. So yeah so I'm
Thropos can is one of these great Greek words. I know we've mentioned before on
the show that biblical authors like
to use because it can have two different shades of meaning and so they can use the word and
imply both. They can kind of use the one word and do a porque no los dos.
I mean my usual example of this is, I'd say John does this all the time, but
is what Saint John does when Christ is talking to Nicodemus, St. Nicodemus in the gospel of John,
And he says famously you must be born again.
or from above, depending on how you read Anothin.
And it seems like he means both.
He's deliberately using that word to convey both ideas.
And St. Paul makes use of this theologically.
And a prime example of this is in Romans chapter 5.
And...
don't get too excited Calvinist friends because this isn't going where you want it to.
Do you think we have any Calvinist listeners left? I think we do. Okay. I think we do. I don't know
if they still want to listen but it's for ordained that they will. They feel compelled somehow.
They must. So if you look at in Romans 5 particularly verses 12 and
and fit.
15, right? This is where St. Paul makes this does this comparison contrast between Adam and Christ.
Right? And he says through one man, right? Sin enters the world and through sin, death and then
contrast that way through one man
Right, and this being Adam and Christ and the word he uses for man there is Anthropos, right?
Yeah, there because yeah, not a near because these are
not just about these two individual,
they're being two individual men, right?
One who did one thing and one who did another thing.
You could make that contrast all kinds of things, right?
Like, can enable, right?
Can enable you have one man who was obedient
and one man who was disobedient,
one man who was righteous and one man who was wicked, right?
You could make that all day long.
But those comparisons are kind of irrelevant
to everyone else.
Hmm, whereas what St. Paul is very
clearly doing in Romans 5 is talking about how these two men Adam and Christ are archetypal men.
Right. These are men whose decisions and actions affect more than just an individual person.
Yeah. Right. That affects humanity, affects what we would call using a little later,
terminology human nature itself right humanity
itself is affected by the actions of these two men.
Right?
And so, in a unique way, St. Paul is setting out Adam and Christ as not just individual
instances of human nature, but as embodying and hypostaticizing the human nature.
in a very particular and special way, beyond the way like I do. Right? And so Adam,
right, by virtue of that, what he does brings death to all of humanity, what Christ does brings life,
right to all of humanity. Yes, all of humanity because remember everyone is raised
the dead on the last day. That's right. Doesn't say anything about what happens after that.
But we will, in a future episode soon, be talking about what happens after that.
Eschatology series, everybody. Which doesn't mean it's the end of the podcast, by the way.
I mean, it could be, but eventually there will be a last podcast. They will.
That's right.
right, but not today. And I mean, it would be ironic if last podcast on the left was the
last podcast, but I think we can outlast them. So they're like Hollywood types. So I mean,
they're going to get mad at each other and break up. Oh, totally. So when St. Paul talks
about the man of lawlessness here, and he uses on Thropos and he uses this language,
He is similarly trying to set up this man of law, isn't it?
as an archetypal figure.
As a figure who, right, there is a person,
but that that person embodies lawlessness
or we could get into what that means, right?
Embodies those things in a unique way
and it has effects beyond just himself.
Yeah, because that's how archetypes work.
Yes.
So, have you covered-
the man part now, the lawlessness part. So the word lawlessness is anomia, which no
most is what gets translated as law in English. That's not a great translation. But you
add a to the front like a that means without, right?
It's a privitive. They can't call him the illegal man.
No, Alfa privitive.
Nope.
person is illegal. So yeah, it's the alpha-privileged if you put it on the front of means, right?
Not. So we have to remember that, as I mentioned, law, not a great translation. Of course, the
original word is Torah and Hebrew, which means teaching. No-most in Greek really means
refers to like a way of
life, and includes ideas, modern ideas of culture, religion,
yeah, folk,
like saying,
forays,
that's their way.
Yeah.
I mean, that that colloquial phrase in English, which has a lot
more to it than just the particular thing you're talking about.
It's that's their way.
Right.
You know,
right.
And the Greeks were cosmopolitan enough to realize that
different peoples in different parts of the world had different ways.
No, yeah.
A different no me.
And so there's a no most of the Greeks, there's a no most of the Egyptians, right?
And they would have philosophical debates.
One of the big philosophical debates in the first century among Greek philosophers was
about which things are by fisi's, by nature, and which things are by no most.
Right?
One of the things that are, for example, naturally right.
What are the things that just we
hold to be right within our no-mose, our way of...
Man made ideas versus sort of laws of nature.
Right, right.
Because what is by nature would affect everyone in the world,
whereas no-mose would be variable in these different places and times.
And so, using nomos, the nomos of the yudai, right, of the people of Jujudai.
right, they're nomos, which was summed up in the Torah, right? This is their way of being in the world.
This is their way of life, right? This is the Jewish way of life, including religion, culture,
dress, all of those things. Make sense, right? It's a word to translate Torah, right? And then the,
The, it's Saint Jerome translates it as Lex.
And Lex at the time.
from St. Jerome used it to translate nomos,
had a broader meaning the way nomos does.
It included all of those things.
Yeah, and even now, there's that very famous phrase
that we like to use as Orthodox,
Lex, Arrandi, Lex, Credendi,
which we don't mean by it,
the legislative law of prayer is the legislative law,
you know, that's not what we mean by.
Right.
That's the way.
The practice, the way,
Yeah.
Yeah, and so again, it made the the Lex Romano's was not just the Roman law code, right?
Included that, but it included a lot of other things too.
Whereas law, and I've been told that even in its original English form law included more
than just like statutory law the way we think about it.
Well, yeah, I mean a classic example of course is the phrase the Dane Law, which is the whole
area of northeastern England that was for a while ruled by
Vikings. Yeah. Yeah. And it was actually referred to the area. It was called the Dane Law. Yeah. Yeah.
So what we're talking about is not just someone who breaks rules. Right. They're breaking the law.
But this is
someone who has sort of thrown off it, especially in the context that St. Paul is using it, right,
where the no-most, when St. Paul talks about it, is talking about the Torah, this is someone who
has thrown off like that way of life, is opposed to that way of life, right? The way of life taught by
by God they have rejected.
And so...
So we have to calculate why does Saint Paul choose this word here?
Because he could have just used the word sin.
I could just call this the man of sin.
And sin and lawlessness do in other authors, other Jewish authors, get used as synonyms.
A good example is in 1 John 3 verse 4.
John says, all sin is lawlessness.
Yeah, he just...
makes them tonight.
Yeah.
So, and St. Paul is not speaking, in terms of second
Thessalonians, to a particularly Jewish-dominated group.
No, probably mostly Greeks, right.
So in some ways, sin might make more sense.
But there's good evidence here that this is a place
where St Paul.
is using the word lawlessness because he's bringing in some of these traditions, the Second
Temple traditions, about the anti-Messiah to bear.
And that's chiefly in the figure of when you look at, if you do just a broad survey,
as is my want of Second Temple Jewish literature on something like this, when they give a name
to, we've talked before on the show how they're
all these different names of different like devil or Satan figures in second-tempo literature
and stuff that we talked about.
Yeah.
We should do an episode on that.
Yeah, I think we've covered a lot of them, but we can always revisit things.
Yeah.
But, you know, obviously the devil, Satan, but also a zazel, a mass Sam-El, a mass-dema in
Jubilee's.
But the one of those that most commonly gets used in reference to the anti-Messiah to the Messiah's
Eschatological opponent is actually Belyal or Belyal
It's grounds differently as many of our folks
I think the accepted English translation or pronunciation is Belyal
That's the norm is Belyal. Yeah
And so there's some debate as
as to the etymology of
Belial. It's not Belial. It's not somebody talking about
bail in the deep South. So there are different ideas, but I think the strongest
case is that it comes from Belial in Aramaic because of the time at which we start
seeing this name used in this context.
We start seeing it used in this context.
text in Aramaic literature.
It is a term that gets used before that, but that's where we start to see it.
And if it is from Belial, it literally means yokless, right?
Not having a yok.
And that yok is a common metaphor for Nomo, Surtora, right?
All the way up through Ben Sirac uses it and then Christ basically quotes Ben Sirac.
it looks like when he famously says, you know, take my yoke upon you for my yoke is easy and my burden is liked. Right.
So the idea that this is the yokeless one, right.
Sort of would establish lawlessness as his defining character. Right.
And so, just to give some examples.
from second-temple Jewish literature.
Jubilee's 15 for 32 describes uncircumcised Gentiles
as the Sons of Belyl.
Which I would say that would make a great biker name.
Another one name.
And also Metal Band, but yeah, another Metal Band,
Sons of Belyl.
The Testaments of the 12 Patriarchs, which for the record?
I think most people who are interested in my book apocrypha think that first
Enic is the most important thing in there and it's not the testaments of the
12 patriarchs is the most important thing in there.
Anyway, that is the Baleothar man.
Who cares what you think?
It's true.
But the testaments of the 12 patriarchs is the most important second-time
Jewish tax for Christians to rate.
especially if you want to understand St. Paul and most of the rest of the New Testament.
But in the test of the 12 patriarchs, the term sons of Balaile is used to refer to idolaters
and the sexually immoral who also are probably uncircumcised Gentiles for the most part,
from the perspective of that book at least.
In the ascension of Isaiah 2 verse 4, in the ascension of Isaiah Balaile is kind of the devil figure
in general.
Hmm.
opposition to Isaiah, but he is described as the angel of lawlessness who is the ruler of this
world, Balaal. And St. Paul actually references, actually uses the name Balaal, transliterates it in
one place. And that's in 2nd Corinthians 615. Yeah, what harmony is there between Christ and Balaal?
Right, and so Christ being again the Greek word for Messiah, right? Messiah and
Belial.
obviously are opposed, right?
Definitionally by this time in terms of the tradition.
But sort of the thing that really clinches the deal
that man of lawlessness is talking about,
man of the aisle is that in Proverbs 6, 12 through 15,
it talks about a Dom Belial, the man of the aisle.
Yeah, so here's what that says.
The man of the aisle, a wicked man goes about
with crooked speech, winks with his eyes,
signals with this
He points with his finger with perverted heart, devises evil, continually sowing discord.
Therefore calamity will come upon him suddenly.
In a moment he will be broken beyond healing.
He's like washing gang signs or clearly.
That's what it is.
Yes, just stipulations are the demons form of sin.
These are actually referring to...
ideas of seduction, of ideas of scoffing and mockery of plotting secretly and conspiring.
But you can see in the language there in Proverbs, the man of Balaile, he here is being referred
to in this archetypal, these archetypal terms.
Right.
That's why it's Adam Belial.
That Adam here is being used for the same kind of general sense.
And so, when St. Paul applies,
to this particular person who's going to emerge
as catalogically, again, he's using an archetypal to say,
this is going to be sort of the ultimate instance
of this type.
But not the only instance of this type.
But this is going to be sort of the ultimate embodiment,
the ultimate encapsulation of this type.
And so then, so man of lawlessness, which I'm
saying is he's applying these manual-polihal traditions as the first title by which St. Paul
refers to this figure. The second one then is the Son of Destruction in the translation
you read. Sometimes Son of Tradition is how it's translated in English. This phrase
occurs one other time in scripture in St. John's Gospel 17 verse 12 to describe.
Christ uses it to describe Judas.
When he says in his prayer that he hasn't lost anyone except
the Son of perdition, the Son of...
Yeah, which it's not super obvious in English that it's upon
because perdition literally means to be the state of being lost.
So I haven't lost any except this lost guy.
Yeah.
Except the Son of being lost.
And of course son of...
Foss boys.
Yeah, son of remember, as we talked about, I know several times on the show, this phrase
son of is a common idiom to refer to, right, the son is the image of the father.
Yeah, right.
And so being the son of something means sort of being the embodiment of that thing, right.
So, Barnabas, Barnabas, the son of encouragement, so he's sort of in a body.
Right. Of poor, uh, poor, uh, poor,
rabbi's on top of everything else. Uh, uh,
Barabas means son of his father. Right.
Jesus father. So yeah, which seems obvious,
but has that meaning like that you just implied. Right.
Right. That he's the image of the bodyman of his dad. Right. Um,
chip, they could call him chip.
So
So if you are the son of, right, being lost
for the son of, right, you're the embodiment of,
right, the sort of destruction damnation.
Right.
But by the way, we just heard from a listener
that sons of Balaal is a metal band from Cleveland.
Oh, they already exist.
Well, it already exists.
It already exists.
And there's apparently two different bands
named sons of tradition.
Oh, hi, oh.
I'm about to alienate a lot of people,
including probably
Many people who work for ancient faith because they live there.
But I recently saw that a priest who's a friend of ours has been sent to a church in Indiana.
And again, I don't care about getting canceled.
Indiana is the poor man, Ohio.
Oh, wow.
I said it.
Crossroads of America.
Anyway, they have, they have the RV Hall of Fame.
I'm sorry, I tried to get out of town.
Wow.
My brother lives in Indiana man.
We just lost a whole swath of his
the analyst.
Calvin is gone. Indiana gone.
Anyway, I mean, you know, our producer is sitting in Indiana
right now.
I know.
I've had it.
I'm out.
This is how little I care.
This is.
Well, you know what else is in Indiana?
Gary.
Okay.
Gary Vienna is a city in India a birth birthplace of one of them of the Greek Orthodox metropolitan of Pittsburgh
He's from Gary and he got out of there and went to pay that should tell anyway. He's a Yins or now
So
Unexpected Indiana. He's a big bail. Yes, address your hate bail in Deanna to father Andrew and to pay
Actually, I have an uncle who lives in Indiana. So
Um.
I went to Notre Dame, relatedly.
So all that aside, being the son of the destruction of the damnation means sort of the embodiment
of it.
And this term, well that's the other place that occurs in the New Testament, is used,
For example, in 2nd Temple literature in Jubilee's 10 verse 3, where the Nephilim are referred
to.
as the sons of perdition or of disjunction. Right. And these are the Nephilim before the flood.
So that is in some ways literal. And hey, we're talking about giants, folks.
So this brings us back to, though, not just thinking about giants and the Nephilim,
But to that whole narrative
that Jubilee's, a lot of Jubilee's is sort of an expanded retelling of Genesis.
And so this is bringing us back to the whole story that unfolds in the genealogy of Cain.
With Cain is sort of the archetypal center who teaches and sort of his evil continues
to snowball down the generations to culminate in lamic, to culminate in the...
the Nephilim, who are these mighty men, who are these God kings, right? So, so they claim.
And so this title calls us back to that idea, right? In terms of referring to the Antichrist,
St. Paul referring to the Antichrist by this title, calls us back to those figures in the
the genesis narrative.
Yeah, it's gonna be like one of these great
ancient demonic demonized humans.
Yes, and I predict that someone right now
is getting ready to dial and call in.
You can call in, but if you're calling in to ask,
does this mean that the Antichrist
will be literally a giant, like from the ritual
and everything, right?
Not necessarily.
Hey, it's not about some kind of special formula.
So yeah, so this is a comparison that St. Paul is making,
Right.
of the type of person who's gonna be could be right maybe he's gonna be a demon worshipping
cannibal right but there have been a fair number of those down the ages but that's not
necessarily what St Paul is getting at here right if that was what he was getting at he could
have just said it yeah the fact that he alludes to it means he's alluding to it right he's sort
of calling that to mind without actually making the statement that yes this is exact.
because of course Judas wasn't.
Literally a nephilim.
That would have been mentioned.
Yes.
That would have been noticed by the other disciples
a lot earlier that him stealing from the money box.
I think.
Right.
Why is this guy 15 feet tall and he keep anyway?
Oh no.
You're going to reignite that for everybody.
Yeah, I'm going to get that all started up again.
I told you I don't care.
I'm just ripping it out.
Yeah, so...
So he is alluding to that kind of evil, right?
That kind of archetypal evil, that kind of embodiment of sin and of rejection of God's teaching and his law, right?
But not not meaning to give us and make any detailed kind of statement, at least in verse three.
Yeah.
And yes, we have just spent the first half of the program on one verse.
Hey, your doctoral dissertation is like what?
900 pages on a third of a verse five five Greek words
Two of which are and in the
All right, well on that colossal
Demon worshiping cannibalistic note we're gonna go ahead and go to our first break and we'll be right back
with the Lord of Spirits
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
MUSIC
Greetings, Pothfathers.
So, my greetings, Pothfathers.
I'm Robin Phillips, the Nostek buster at Ancient Faith.
Did you know that God's Kingdom is of this earth?
Did you know that the resurrection totally changed history?
Did you know that because of Christ's substitutionary tonement, we can build for God's kingdom?
Do you know that as we participate in God's kingdom building work, we make the world
a better place?
If any of these questions surprise you, it could be because you have been unconsciously
tinctured with some form of implicit narcissism.
But that's okay. I used to be a Gnostic and then my latest book, Re Discovering the Goodness
of Creation. I have shared my journey from Gnosticism to Orthodox Christianity. It's a journey
I invite you all to travel with me. Re Discovering the Goodness of Creation is available at
store.ancientfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Steven
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Case you're wondering what that greetings podfathers was,
we don't know.
Someone was talking to us.
They're not sure.
They're terribly mysterious.
Yes.
uh... leanie bruce still not afraid work
Check the many I have two come here meter first that commercial we just heard you should buy that book
Uh
The forward I wrote for that book is only three pages
So buy it for the book
like my
Forward contribution is like
That like half an Oreo that they stick on top of the cake
like in the corner.
Yeah, I mean, it's a good, it might be a good ice you a little to get that cake instead of another cake size of a book. It's a size you're getting it for the cake. Yeah, get it for the cake.
And number two before the break, I like how every time you mentioned my dissertation, it gets longer.
It's an up to 900 pages. I'm nothing if not hyperbolic.
You're just, yeah, I'm pretty, pretty soon it's gonna be like a 20 volume set of books.
Well, I mean, to me, that is the epitome of a dictionary.
My favorite dictionary is over 20 volumes, rather large volumes.
So I remember when I first encountered that when I was under graduate, I was like, there's
a dictionary that's this big.
And then I found it that Tolkien had worked on parts of it.
I mean, you are the sort who has a favorite dictionary.
I believe in that.
It is, it is...
Like we're talking about anthroposis being like the archetypal man, the Oxford English
dictionary is the archetypal dictionary.
So does that require you to execrate the name of Noah Webster?
Like are you?
Is that just pathetic?
I mean, you know, the Webster's dictionary is fine.
It's fine.
I mean, I want the kind of dictionary that goes on for two.
pages about the shades of meaning of the word have. You know what you say fine is
that dog in a burning house. It's fine. Or no it's just like if you need you know
it's okay. It's okay. But the OED I mean it is one of the most magnificent
pieces of scholarship ever assembled on any subject. And I'm not being hyperbolic
at all on any subject on any subject yeah yeah
Anyway, yes, you can call us 8553U.
It's 8552372346.
And this, this, this show has all the excitement of the Oxford English Dictionary.
Find someone out there, people, people listening, find someone who loves you.
The way Father Andrew loves the Oxford English Dictionary.
It's true.
I mean, I have one right here in my spirit.
I'm sorry.
So, let's move on to verse 4, shall we?
Yes, that's the verse 4.
Okay, yes.
It's like a Thessalonians chapter 2 verse 4.
So this is continuing on about the man of lawlessness in the Soedal Kama, who opposes and
exalts himself against everything called a God or object of piety so that he takes his
seat in the temple of God proclaiming himself to be God or a God.
Yes. So this is now, we're moving on from ways in which St. Paul describes this guy,
this guy being the antichrist, to what this figure is going to do.
Right. And.
The way you just read that is probably different than what a lot of folks will find if they look this up in an English Bible.
Yeah.
We've got that phrase, so called God.
Right.
Which, right.
Like so called in English, like the word, I think the Greek word it literally means as an, is called this way, right?
Yeah.
Called in this manner.
But English so called has this tinge of sarcasm to it.
Yes.
Right.
Which the Greek doesn't.
And that's a deliberate thing, right?
Because it's based on...
based on this, this is really going to the way back machine. This assumption that like Jews
and early Christians were monotheists in a modern sense. Yeah. That they thought that
the Zeus, whatever, didn't exist rather than thinking they were demonic powers, which,
of course, the latter being the case. And so St. Paul, he does the same thing in
first Corinthians when he says, you know, there are many things called gods and many lords,
Right? That gets it? Many so-called gods, right?
in a lot of English translations because of that.
But that's not what it says.
So in this case also, he opposes an exult
to self against everything called a god or object of piety.
And why is that phrasing, that particular phrasing
is important because in that first clause there,
St. Paul is not referring to God himself yet.
The singing box, he refers to God, capital G. Yeah, so the idea is first clause. He's he's putting himself above
everything that's
divine or worshiped or venerated
right right
and
so this is
The way he describes it he is making a contrast deliberately
At a good place to compare
right? That is at least Pauline, we won't have this whole argument.
now, but is Hebrews 2 verses 7 through 9 and the way that interprets a particular verse
in light of Christ?
Yes, so this should be familiar to everybody.
You made him for a little while lower than the angels.
You have crowned him with glory and honor, putting everything in subjection under his feet.
Now, in putting everything in subjection to him, he left nothing outside his control.
present, we do not yet see everything in subjection to him.
but we see him who for a little while was made lower than the angels, namely Jesus,
crowned with glory and honor because of the suffering of death, so that by the grace of God,
he might taste death for everyone.
Right. So Christ here, the pattern with Christ is that Christ
He is the greatest, subjects himself, even below the angels.
Things that are called gods by the nations.
objects of piety, holy ones. He puts himself underneath all that and then is
crowned with glory and honor is exalted by God, the Father. So look again at how
St. Paul describes the Antichrist, the Antichrist opposes and exalts himself
against all of those things.
So this is an inversion.
of what Christ does.
Right?
Same things to be true of the second clause.
So, that says that he takes his seat in the temple of God
is how it's usually pronounced.
And this is God's capital G.
The article is used.
Right? This is one of the signals in Greek
when you're, especially with Jewish authors, obviously,
about whether we're talking about,
when you have all the theos in this case.
It's a genitive, it's tooth-ew.
But the article to indicate this is capital G, God.
So he takes a seat at the temple of God, capital G.
So a lot of our dispensationalist friends
want to take this very literally.
Right, so this means...
that okay the temple in Jerusalem is going to be rebuilt at some point and the
Antichrist is going to go and literally sit in it. Yes. In a chair and they're
going to sacrifice animals to him or something. Yes. I grew up with some of that.
Yeah, so, but this sort of is a very overly literal and a contextual read, right?
because we have to talk about what does it mean to sit in the ancient context?
Yeah, I mean, sitting was not just sitting.
Yeah, you see like a depiction of a bunch of people and one of them is sitting.
But one who's sitting is the one in charge.
Yes. Yeah.
Sitting was a mark of rank.
Right. It was a mark of honor and superiority.
So in the, you know, this is not what people are used to.
it churches now, right? In churches now, pretty much across the board, not just orthodox churches,
when the time comes for the homily, the priest or pastor, whomever, whoever's preaching is standing
up and everyone else sits down. I know, I think we need to get this back to the way that used to be.
Right. And in the ancient world, in the ancient church it was the exact opposite.
Yeah, right. Yeah, which I mean it fit that philosophical model, right? You know with the teacher
the philosopher sitting and all of his disciples standing around him and listen.
Right. And he sits because he's he's the one in authority. This is why we have a bishop's
seat chair thrown in the church. Right. He is the one who sits because he's
the one in the position of authority. Right. And so to sit in someone's presence.
Right. We still do this. This is a practice of the Orthodox Church
that you know.
a bunch of people are sitting in the bishop walks into the room everybody stands up
right or they're supposed to yeah right out of respect right and then usually he you know it
gives you a blessing and tells you to sit back down and he goes and sit down but but this is a
this is a sign of honor and respect still so to remain seated mean if you or if you walk into someone's
presence and you sit down first that saying either I am an authority over you or I'm at least
your equal.
I'm at least your peer, right?
And one of the ways in which you see in the Talmud,
we've talked before on the show about the idea
of two powers in heaven in the second temple period,
and how that relates to the later Christian
doctrine of the Trinity,
but one of the ways in which later rabbinic Judaism
sort of got rid of that idea. It said that idea was wrong.
Is in a story that's recounted in the Talmud about a particular rabbi who has this vision where he's taken up to heaven.
And he sees this figure, this angelic figure who is sitting.
And since he's sitting in heaven in the presence of God, this rabbi believes, oh, this is the second power in heaven.
Um, and then
finds out he was horribly wrong and the angel who had the gall to sit down gets
taken and whipped. But that gives you an idea. That gives you an idea of what it
means to sit. So the word here that's translated as temple is known which is used
in the Greek Old Testament tradition to translate by-
or bait in Hebrew, which could mean temple or can mean house.
And so the idea here is that this is a person who would dare to sit in the presence of God,
capital G. Yeah. IE, he makes himself equal to God, capital G. Right. So this is sort of the
the height of hubris and pride in arrogance.
against. Again, contrast from St. Paul, compare this to Philippians 2 verses 6 through 11,
sometimes called the Carman Christy. We're talking about Christ. He did not consider equality
with God something to be grasped, be held onto, but humbled himself, taking on the form
of a servant. Right? So again each of these clauses.
is an example when we compare it to the example of Christ,
an inversion of who Christ is.
The Antichrist is not someone who humbles himself
and then is exalted, but someone who exalts himself.
As highly as anyone could ever exalt themselves.
Right, with the most hubris possible,
is what we're getting at here.
He doesn't have to go and sit on a particular spot
in Jerusalem to do that, right?
So then St. Paul continues, right? And he sort of comes back to this idea we saw at the beginning
of verse three of the apostasyah, right, that there's this desertion. There are some people
out of post and they deserve it, or they retreat from it, right, or fall away from it.
So this he picks up that idea again.
in verse 6. Okay, so I'm going to read verses 6 and 7. And you know what is restraining him now
so that he may be revealed in his time. For the mystery of lawlessness is already at work. Only
he who now restrains it will do so until he is out of the way. Well, that can also be read as
only that which now restrains it will do so until it or that thing is out of the way.
Because not necessarily he, it's a sort of
that. Right. It's a masculine article being used as a demonstra of pronoun basically. Yeah.
So it can be he who or it could be that witch. Yeah. Right. Because of course language gender.
Right. And so yeah, that translation had restraining or restraint or a restrainer if we're going to
to make it more, something more with agency.
Others have like an impediment, other English translations.
And the word there that's getting translated as a restrainer or a restraint or an impediment
is actually the Greek word, Kata-Kon, which again, Kata means to hold from, which again,
that doesn't help you. But this is also a term
that has a military usage.
Um, um, Codacon is used to refer to like an occupying force or a garrison of troops,
right, a stationed set of troops.
And this of course, fits very much with the term, opposed to Sia, with the uh, Stihita
at the end, right, the stand, right, Aguela.
So there is this.
occupying force, there is this, right, garrison, that is there right now and that then is
going to, right, in some way, treat defect at which time he'll be revealed.
Now, most of the translations is...
we already mentioned have something like restraint or impediment or
restrainer. When you read the church fathers on this, they also use that kind of
language when they elaborate on it of a restrainer or of an impediment, right?
But this is another case where right those those two ideas are not like opposed
to each other. Right. That
That what is it what is a garrison of troops do?
Like why would you garrison troops in a city? Yeah to prevent an uprising basically right to prevent an uprising or an invasion
Yeah, what are the two right or both?
Yep right to keep the peace right you have you have a garrison troops there to
Restrain impede certain things from happening to block certain things from happening. Yeah, right so
So those ideas are not at all.
with each other. Right. So then we have this idea. So we have this imagery that St. Paul's using. We have this sort of garrison, whatever it is that is taking this stand.
Right. That it has not been so that the man of lawlessness has not been revealed. All right. But notice he says that the mystery of lawlessness is already at work.
Hmm, the mystery of lawlessists is at work.
This force is sort of impeding it from taking effect, but eventually it will retreat and
then sort of the mystery of lawlessness will have its way and this figure will emerge.
Right, because it was no longer any restraint.
Right, once that impediment is gone, once they're gone.
Right.
So imagine if you have this garrison of troops in a city, someone wants to invade the city,
can't admit.
the city because there's this garrison of troops, but then the troops withdraw. Now they can have at the city.
And so this language of the mystery of lawlessness already being at work in the world is very much
in keeping with what St. Paul says elsewhere, about the power of evil in the world.
Right, so just as a couple examples, right, second Corinthians 4 verse 4, St. Paul refers to the god of this age, right, doing evil.
It's a way of referring to the devil as, right, having some kind of rulership being operational in this world.
Ephesians 2 verse 2, you refers to St. Louis the Prince of power of the air.
And of course, the language ruler of this world gets used repeatedly in St. John's Gospel
in John 1231, 14 verse 30, 16 verse 11, and that's Christ.
Yeah, now the ruler of this world is judged to that kind of thing.
Right. Referring to the devil as the ruler of this world or this age.
Right. Not the age to come.
All right.
And so that's very much sort of the idea.
that St. Paul is getting at when he talks about this mystery of lawlessness already being operational, right?
But it can't sort of come to a head until this, opposed to Sia, this retreat, this breaking of camp, right?
Happens, right?
Literally, Katakone means to, I mean, if you want to take a really literal thing of it, it's depart from the middle, right?
to leave the midst but that's as I did a brake camp to pick up and move.
And you pointed out that removed.
Right. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Some translations have it as, you know, this, um,
Restrainer is removed.
And the problem with that is that,
in 21st century English.
Remove is almost always
used in a transitive way.
And so people take it that way.
Like it means that something is going to get moved out
of the way by something else.
But there's this older use, this intransitive use
of remove.
I shall now remove myself to my bed.
You know, that you can, or I shall now remove, you know,
meaning I'm leaving.
You know, it doesn't necessarily mean someone removed me.
I can remove myself.
I can just leave.
Yeah.
Right.
And so we shouldn't conclude from that, even if you're
reading the
translation in that way. That's why the translation you read said is out of the way. That's actually more accurate. Yeah. Yeah.
But that removed until it is removed, it would seem to apply that, oh, some person is going to come and remove that
restrainer. Right. Yeah. It's not really what the original is getting at. Yeah. So what is going on then with this
with this military garrison, this military unit.
So part of this is that a major linkage, particularly when it comes to this imagery of Christ
versus Antichrist, Messiah versus Antim Messiah, Messiah versus Baleil, has to do with the priesthood,
and with the priest
understood in military terms. Yeah. Which is very foreign to us today. Yes, we're not
really big on on Templars and such. Yeah, these days. Yeah. So, right, like now, you know,
in the US military, and I think in most militaries, right, chaplains are non-combatants. They
don't bear arms right. The while
there may be some sort of metaphorical references to onward Christian soldiers and this sort
of thing, and even to priestly rank. But we don't conceive of the priesthood in military
terms. But of course, the scriptures very much do. And that's something that either we're
not aware of or if we're aware of it it often makes us uncomfortable frankly.
because there is throughout the Hebrew Scriptures,
they're supposedly mainly on the Torah,
but we could do more.
The priesthood is referred to in this military terms
that are a lot more like a D&D cleric
than like Father Mokahi on Mash.
Yeah, I mean,
like the idea that clergy are supposed
to be sort of personally...
I mean, that's that as a canonical basis as well now, right?
Like there's cannons basically saying that we can't, you know, bear arms.
Right.
We're not here pro-Zellatory.
We don't think priests should go out start massacring people for the record.
Right.
Yeah.
The point here is the disappointment of certain people on Twitter.
It's true.
The point is that this is a thing in the scriptures.
And it was regarded as normal, you know, at this ancient period.
and...
This starts with Levi himself. Right? Genesis 34, the one major episode we get in the life of Levi
the person, after whom the tribe was later named, is him along with Simeon mastermindening the revenge
against the men of Shechem for the rape of their sister Dino Ordena. So Levi's revenge, there's another
Melban name or amusement park ride. Yeah, unless Levi Strauss company suits you. So be careful
Right, but so he go they go remember this episode to get revenge they they go and
It's revenge through conversion they go and talk all of the all of the checker bites into being circumcised
Yeah, and then while the adult men are recovering from being circumcised they go through a massacre of them all
And so then when we get later into the tribe of Levi and we've talked about this on
the show before, but the tribe of Levi receives the priesthood in Exodus 32 after in verses
26 through 29 after the episode with the golden calf, they go and slaughter 3,000 elders
of the people who had been serving as priests before the
who had worshiped the Golden Caff.
In this Golden Caff episode, it was of course
at the time that Moses received the Torah,
received the law, making this the first Pentecost.
And so now we're gonna say something nice
about Brian Zahn, of all people.
Look him up, everybody.
Or don't.
Yeah, or don't.
And he says, to be fair,
the nice thing was that he pointed something out,
something out.
He did it in a very inarticulate and theologically weird way.
So not even endorsing the way he stated it.
But he did helpfully point out credit where credit is due that there were 3000 priests
killed at the first Pentecost and at the second Pentecost in the Book of Acts, there were
3000 people who became followers of Christ.
There you go.
So same number.
So that was a helpful observation.
he made. Yeah, that's what I said about it. I much prefer the music of Eric's on to
anything from Brian's on. Let me move on to Phineas. So we've talked about before or Pinias
in numbers 25 versus one through 13. He and his descendants, he's a grandson of Aaron.
and his descendants are given the high priesthood because he's the one who goes and
puts the spear through the fornicating people at Baal Paor and puts an end to the rebellion there.
And a very important though, beyond just these sort of massacres, a very important military
image for these purposes, for what we're talking about here in terms of what St. Paul is doing
is actually relates to Aaron, right?
The original...
the original high priest, the originator of the Levitical priesthood.
And this is at numbers 16 versus 46 through 48.
Yes, two references to the book of numbers in one half of the show.
And this is where, after the rebellion of Korra, which we've talked about before at some length,
right. Coral remembers the guy who shows up and says, why are Aaron and these other priests?
putting themselves over us. Aren't we all priests?
Understand that as you will.
And then the ground sloths them up.
Aaron, a plague breaks out and Aaron is called to stand in the
midst, to stand between the dying of the dead and the living
With his sensor, with his incense being offered
to God. And so he stands in the midst in the middle point between life and death
to ward off and put an end to the plague. And when this is interpreted in the
book of Wisdom which was written later in Greek, now a whole bunch of people are
going to freak out because I'm saying it wasn't written by Solomon. Solomon
wasn't alive in the first century AD and he didn't write in Greek and the
church fathers, the first ones who mentioned it say that the book of Wisdom was part
of the New Testament.
New Testament because it was written in Greek in the first century.
Anyway.
Yep.
But wisdom, 18, which is now part of our Old Testament, but originally written in Greek,
wisdom 18 verse 21 through 25, go back and describe this episode in the life of Aaron.
Aaron. Yeah, so this is what it says for a blameless man.
man, was quick to act as their champion. He brought forward the shield of his ministry,
prayer and propitiation by incense. He would stood the anger and put an end to the disaster,
showing that he was thy servant. He conquered the wrath not by strength of body and not
by force of arms, but by his word he subdued the Punisher, appealing to the oaths and covenants
given to our fathers. For when the dead had already fallen on one another in heaps, he intervened
and held back the raft and cut off its way to the living.
For upon his
long robe the whole world was depicted and the glories of the fathers were engraved in the four
rows of stones and thy majesty on the diadem upon his head to these the destroyer yielded,
these he feared, for merely to test the wrath was enough. It's interesting the, you know,
plague is here depicted not as a kind of impersonal force, but as the destroyer.
Right. Resha, yeah, we've, yeah.
Yeah, that's now right.
Play is this.
This is sort of demonic force that's out there at work.
And this military language is used, the shield of his ministry, the be their champion.
This military language is used for what Aaron is doing in standing in the midst and warding
this off.
Right.
And it's pretty epic scene blocking.
And kind of resonant with what St. Paul is saying.
in terms of this impediment.
Yeah, the restrainer.
Right. And this restrainer.
This, this garrison, right, that,
that wards off and, and protects.
And we can see how this is
integrated particularly into
these traditions with the Messiah and
Belial in one Q Melchizedek,
which is one of the Dead Sea Scrolls.
The number is the cave it was found in.
So
found in KF1 Q for cumeron that lets you know it's a Dead Sea scrolled and then
Melchizedek because that's who it's about just to give you the references real
quick two versus one through three, 15 versus four through seven and 16 versus
13 and 14 if you want to look those up but describe Melchizedek coming as the
Messiah so Melchizedek is the Messianic figure we talked about the scroll a
little bit back in the Melchizedek episode but Melchizedek coming as the
Messiah.
and he leads an army of priests, of his priests, because Mount Kizadek, of course, is a priest,
against Belyl and his armies. So all of this, Ellen, the priesthood is for St. Paul and the
tradition he's received bound up in, right, the idea of this conflict between the Messiah and Belyl,
between Christ and Antichrist. And so the impediment here
or the restrainer is priestly sacrificed.
It's Christian worship.
Put a fine point out it's the Eucharist.
It's the offering of incense,
just like it was with Aaron.
Then you can see as you read through
Second Thessalonians 2 through the whole chapter,
there's this backdrop of worship.
Being talked about, who is worshiped,
what is worshiped, what is the object of piety?
Yeah.
St. Paul does not speak of the Antichrist here
in political terms, primarily.
Right.
Of course, there was no separation between politics and religion at this time, but from our
perspective, right?
Yeah, it's idolatry versus piety.
Right.
It's in religious terms, right here.
And he talks about toward the end of the chapter how those who were not willing to accept
the truth, and it's the religious truth, to accept the yoke, to accept the Torah, right,
except the teaching, the...
the way of being in the world that Christianity represents,
that they were in rejecting that,
were handed over to delusion.
Right?
What is that delusion?
That's the mystery of lawlessness that's out there in the world.
Right?
What protects from it?
What is keeping the world going, keeping the world alive,
keeping the end from coming?
Right?
Now, someone may point out
if they're not on the line to do it on.
or any, doesn't sound like it.
That a number of the church fathers, St. John Christophe,
prominent among them, when they talk about this impediment
or a strainer, they talk about the Christian monarchy
that started with St. Constantine.
And so some people will get in there and say,
oh, the father's saying that it's the Christian monarchy.
And...
There are a lot of folks in the 20th century who took a very literal direct interpretation
of that. They said, well, the last czar is gone. There's no more Christian monarch.
Therefore, this is the end times. Now the Antichrist is going to be revealed. Some of them took
it very literally. And that was Lenin or Stalin. Yeah. Yeah. So by the way, so since you mentioned that,
we do have a caller. Oh, calling. Yeah. Yeah. So is he calling to make that point? I don't know. I
I don't know, we'll find out, I guess we're...
or she, it is it is a coming off in sexist this episode.
In fact, a she.
We have Janine calling.
So Janine, are you there?
Yes, I'm here.
Welcome, Gloria Spears podcast.
Janine, what is on your mind?
OK, well, I started out with one question
that I got so interested in what you're talking about.
I have another one.
But my main basic question was, in terms of the anti-Christ
and son of Billiole in the arts.
types of terms that you've been discussing as representing evil and its forms in the world.
Does that mean that when we see those forms of evil in the world such as violence or a
coercive power that's abused or, you know, manipulation, lying and so on and so forth,
lawlessness, as you say? Does that mean that we should understand that as the Antichrist
at work in the world and also your
for sure tell us to expect that these things will get worse as sort of time goes on.
And then I was also got interested in that you were speaking about the military terms.
You made me think about the word Legion use for the man who was occupied by Legion of demons.
And Greek of course, you hear military terms use for angels like Tux-Yarchus or Archangel.
So I was wondering how those things are linked as well.
those are my two questions.
Those are great questions.
Thank you.
Yeah. I mean, to the first thing, right, like,
on one level, I'll just say,
we'll listen to the third half.
Okay. I'll just say,
I'm going to say that.
That's good. That means you're tracking with us.
That's right. That's right.
I love it. What are the listeners do that?
Yeah.
So, yeah, I mean, we're going to talk about that,
like, especially this question of,
is there something coming?
you know, do-
are there signs to recognize?
We're gonna talk about that.
But yeah, I don't know Father, like Legion,
I mean, it is actually interpreted,
like Legion says for we are many, right?
There's this explanation of why this is the name.
Like this guy or two guys,
depending on which gospel you're reading,
possessed by a big pile of demons.
But I mean is there a kind of
inverted, is this an inversion of the Katech one? Like this guy's being, he's, he's being
garrisoned by demons. I don't know. What do you think, Father?
Well, yeah, that is, that is sort of the imagery, right? Like we, we use the term
possessed. So, if we're kind of lost, what that means, right? To go in and take possession
of something, right? Like the Israelites went in and took possession of the land, right?
And these demons have gone in and taken possession of this person.
Yeah, like like there are two
Brian him. Yeah, yeah, and they
they don't intend to leave.
Right?
And yeah, and so yeah, this
this spiritual warfare language
right is is is not there's
there's not a distinction between
liturgy and spiritual warfare.
Those are not two different things.
different things.
Right, like the and this is sort of what that that passage we read from wisdom is getting at that sort of the weapons of Aaron's warfare.
Right, it's the plague, which is sort of embodying described as this evil power. Right is his sensor is that incense that he's offering to God.
is worship, right? And so, yeah.
So there's not a disconnect there, right?
And the military language that's used about the angels
is not at odds with them as the worshipers of God
perpetually in heaven who are serving
in the heavenly sanctuary.
Yeah, because I mean, if the big conflict
is over idolatry versus piety,
than to be pious in the Christian sense.
of worshiping the one true God is an attack against idolatry.
Yes, yeah. We make war against the demons with our prayers.
Right, the full armor of God, Saint Paul says.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. And so these things are very much meshed, meshed together.
Yeah, as you say.
Well, thank you so much, Father. You also remind me that Christ spoke of the image of
The stronger man
who takes the strong man's house,
that also seems to be at military image.
Yeah. Yeah.
Thank you so much, fathers.
Thanks for calling, Janine. Thank you.
Yeah.
You know, another thing that occurred to me
when she mentioned possession, right?
See, I am going to use a little,
throw in a little old English.
I could go. Yeah. Right.
So so a couple of military
terms from Old English, Heldon, which is the ancestor of our word hold, which we still
used to refer to military action of holding the battlefield.
Yeah, we're building.
Yeah, right.
Yeah.
It still has that sense of occupation, but then you've also got the word, well, then, which
is the ancestor of our word, wield.
And you literally, like a king literally wields his kingdom in Old English and a Trump in
general wheels of the battlefield.
as well. So there's not just a sense of possession, but also like making use of, you know, at the same time. So, um,
yeah, it's interesting like how much deeper that sense is, then, as you said, our modern notion of possession.
But if you look, if you again sort of re-literalize it back to possessing, having holding, wielding, commanding, um, it all works.
It all works.
Yeah.
So, the ZAR back to the Christian, you said the ZAR right?
Yes.
So from what I started back to SCA and it had yelled his off.
And so the first cut is the deepest.
Maybe I know.
First Cat Stevens reference of the night
So, right, so there were people who took that very literally in the early 20th century,
right, that the last czar has been murdered, Lenin or Stalin, right, is the Antichrist now
revealed.
Now obviously that is not panned out, right, to be the case.
that those figures weren't antichrist, more on that in the third half.
but the terms of being V, right, the final, the ultimate, right.
And so, and I think that's from a slight
misinterpretation of the fathers, or
misinterpretation might be the wrong word.
It might just be an overly literal read,
because I think what the fathers were getting at,
And the reason I think this gets
that's read overly literally is again a context issue.
So for most of the fathers we're talking about,
even like St. John Chrysostom.
St. John Chrysostom is in Constantinople
like 20 years after Christianity
became the official religion of the empire
less than 20 years, actually when he starts,
when he first goes to Constantinople.
when we're talking about the saints of the
century, a lot of them had been alive during the period of persecution during the final great
persecutions. And so what St. Constantine's conversion to Christianity represented to them,
what the Adosius represented to them is a little different than what the emperor in the 11th
13th or 14th century, or the Russians are represented.
A little different.
In that, the conversion of St. Constantine and the subsequent early Christian
empires of the fathers were dealing with, represented a transformation and an
establishment of the Christian religion as religion, meaning Christian
practices, Christian worship, right, in the world, in a way that it had not been
before.
Right? So already St. Constantine puts an end to pagan sacrifices in the military and
puts an end to pagan sacrifices as a public work, which is what liturgy means, by the way,
public work, not the work of the people, public work done by the government, by a ministry
of the government. And makes the Eucharist a public work. He makes the Eucharist liturgy.
by making it a public work. He establishes it within the military, he establishes it within
the civil order, that of course then gets furthered by subsequent Christian emperors.
And so this to them is what the Christian monarchy represents to them vis-à-vis...
Christian worship. The Christian mark is the guarantee that the Eucharist will continue
to be served. That sacrifices will continue to be offered. In sense, will continue to be
offered with prayers at every place. Because we have this Christian monarch who is there
to ensure it. And so what we're here proposing about the liturgy and the service of the liturgy
Christian worship being the repent.
impediment is not at odds with the idea that the Christian monarchy is related to that.
Right? This is again a porcane of those. Don't simply understand the fathers who say this in their
context. Right? They're saying if the Christian monarchy goes away and persecution begins again,
right, then that persecution will begin to put a stop to the Eucharist. And if this worship of
God ceases, right, in the world that
will bring about the time of the end. That will bring about the time of the end. And especially with,
as we said, and we're going to develop that a little more in the third half also,
with St. Paul appealing to this image of the Nephilim of these ancient God kings,
as the image of who the Antichrist is going to be.
That becomes sort of the image.
image. There is this contrast because, of course, again, those who are alive before St.
Constantine's conversion saw a God king in the Roman emperor. This was not like ancient
history for them. This was not ancient, crazy history, right? Like if Joe Biden came
out tomorrow and claimed he was a God, people would say, okay, he finally lost his marbles.
right. But in the ancient world people like shuffle him off. Yeah, that's what emperors are.
Yes. So, so, so, right. So this was and this is in living memory, but there were these God
kings. Right. And so if this is your image of the Antichrist, right, St. Constantine represents
it a departure from that because not only did he put an end to those pagan sacrifices, he
He was as the Roman Emperor.
when he became emperor, the Pontifex Maximus, he was the high priest of the Roman religion.
But not only does he not practice the pagan sacrifices himself as would have been his duty as emperor,
but he does not take any Christian ecclesiastical office for himself.
Yeah, which he theoretically could have done. I mean, there would have been tried to, but yeah,
Yeah, right? He doesn't try to make himself a bishop. He never tried.
to serve the Eucharist, he never tried to offer incense. Right? Never even tried. Right? He
separates those things from himself, even as a Christian. And so again, someone like St. John
Chrysostom living at the time he lived, right? If this Christian monarchy goes away meaning,
This gets replaced by a pagan monarch.
You're going to be right back into this God-king territory, antichrist territory.
And so this makes sense in that original context.
And this is why Julian the Apostate becomes the image of the antichrist for almost all
of the church fathers.
When you see the church fathers, I mean, take John of Damascus as a perfect example.
When you read his precise exposition of the
Orthodox faith and you read everything he says about the Antichrist and the Antichrist
is going to do.
It's all stuff that Julian the Apostate did and tried to do.
Yeah, and centuries after Julian.
Yes.
Yeah.
But what is Julian the Apostate?
He's the pagan emperor who came along and tried to reverse what the Christian emperor had
done.
Yeah.
Right.
And so that's why they're connecting the...
the Christian monarchy with with the impediment right so the liturgy as
anyone who's ever been to an Orthodox liturgy knows is about asking for God's
mercy right because we've talked many times on the show about how justice works
and injustice right justice is everything being in its place and operating
correctly injustice is when that order gets broken and then just
is when that order gets restored and sometimes it's a violent correction.
Right. And that for God there is always this, you can see it like a balance scale. Right.
On one hand there are the victims of evil in the world who are crying out for justice,
starting with the blood of Abel. Right. And the widows and the orphans and the souls of the
martyrs caught right.
out how long oh lord, right? And then on the other hand, on the other side is God's mercy and his
patience to allow people time to repent. And different language gets used for this in the
scriptures. One of the most common is, you know, the cup of the iniquity of this people is not fully
yet. And then it gets full. And that's gale tips. And it tips away from mercy. And it tips toward
judgment toward these things being correct.
And so nations fall, cities get destroyed by flaming meteors.
Things happen and things are corrected.
And this is true on the macro scale also.
This is what Saint Peter says.
He says, Christ is not delaying his coming.
God has not forgotten about you and all the things you're suffering in this world.
But he is patient.
He is merciful.
He is allowing people time to repent.
time to repent but the day will come for the whole world.
When that scale tips and that's when the final the final judgment will happen and so
Reason and liturgy we're asking for God to have mercy so much right is that we're offering the liturgy
We're offering the sacrifice of the Eucharist for the life of the world and for its salvation
Right that is what is keeping this world going
Right the prayers and worship of God's people asking him for mercy for more time to repent
for
more time to make things right before the end and the judgment comes.
And so ultimately, what St. Paul is getting at here with this idea of the impediment or the
restrainer is that the end of liturgy will be the end of the world.
That when the worship of God ceases, and this is what Christ is referring to, he says,
when the Son of Man comes, we'll find faith on the earth.
Yeah, we find worship happening basically.
Right.
When that ceases and that fails, that's when the end comes.
As for the man of lawlessness, St. Paul says in verse 8, how he ends up when Christ appears.
And then the lawless one will be revealed, whom the Lord Jesus will kill with the breath
of his mouth and bring to nothing by the appearance of his coming.
Yes.
and
Yes, you should understand the breath of his mouth in terms of the Holy Spirit.
Hmm.
The members of the fire of the Holy Spirit.
Nice.
Which is purifying, right?
And so he also will meet his end.
So yeah, so in our third and final half, we'll talk about what St. John has to say about
the end of Christ in this figure and how he fleshes out what we've already seen in
St. Paul.
Yeah.
Yeah, cool.
We have a caller on the line, but we're going to get to him
right after our break.
So we'll be right back with a third half.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
video.
But one thing is needed, and Mary has chosen that good part, which will not be taken away from her, Luke 10, verse 42.
Mary's choice to receive life-giving words at Jesus' feet, hints at Martha's real need.
When one's material needs consume all one's attention, nothing more will be sought after.
The demands of physical life can totally colonize the mind.
Jesus desired to redirect Martha's concerns toward spiritual things.
She had prioritized food over him, although a bare morsel of bread in his hands could turn
into lamb.
Spiritual life has its own logic.
And that logic tells you that, if you are in need of many things, and there is one who
is the source of all things, you must seek that one.
and the many will be provided.
to you. In Christ we find the mystery of sufficiency and of surplus. So if sufficiency in everything
is what you desire and surplus to, then empty your heart of its clutter and offer it to
him.
The story of Jesus by Matthew the poor
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father-anger-Steven-Damic and Father-Steven
young.
If you have a question call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everybody.
We're talking about the man of lawlessness, the Antichrist, him or herself.
You don't want to be sexist.
See, nobody ever says he or she when you're talking about the Antichrist.
I know.
I love, I mean, it was totally happening.
with it being a dude. I mean, I do like to point out, I do like to point out to people that
the devil in Norse mythology is female. Heela, you know, Heela. Yeah. Well, the God of the
dead. Yeah, right, right. The God of the dead. Yeah. I mean, Kate Blanchett, right? Yeah.
All right. Well, we do have, we do have a caller on the line. And I said he, but actually,
the the the caller boards is Chris so I don't know Chris
Are you there? Welcome to Laura Spirits. I'm here. Okay, so you are here. All right. You're just
misgendering our callers now. I don't know. So many microabessions. Talk about lawlessness.
So I had a question concerning something Father De Young said. He said that the end of the world
comes with the end of liturgy or when liturgy ceases.
Am I characterizing?
not correctly. Yes. Okay. Now that seems different than what I saw in the 1999 TBN film Omega Code.
Yeah. Yeah. The newly departed Mary and Robertson and I had a slight disagreement on that.
Wasn't it this morning Pat Robertson died? Yeah. Pat Robertson died just today. Yeah. Yeah.
Wow, so it's not like that is what you're saying.
It is not.
Okay, there are also no codes in the Bible only in movie what only in movie dick
In fact, there's a page in movie dick where it is encoded that there are no codes in the Bible only in movie
Okay, well this changes everything I
It's all good back to seminary. Okay. Yeah, I appreciate it one more question
Father Dionne, have you played any add?
I have not but my wife has been playing it.
It looks amazing.
So yeah, it seems good.
Ed, she's, she's got some kind of, she was in the stress test in the beta.
So, and she's got some craft cross platform thing going on between her Xbox Series X and her computer.
Wow. Wow.
Yeah, one shit.
Okay, that's it.
Well, it was a good film.
I was helping you all just got.
Yeah, no, no, no. I'm more likely to discuss the Nick Cage remake of Left Behind.
Oh, I have so family's traditional.
I know, but Nick Cage is Nick Cage.
It's true.
But that movie's only like a tenth of a Mandy.
That's true.
You know what I'm.
We should do our own MST3K version of the Nicholas cage love.
behind that word of spirit. Yeah. Yeah. That would be fun. All right. Okay. That's it. Thanks for
calling Chris. All right. Well, welcome to the third half, everybody. Um, finally got through
second us Lonions chapter two. Some of it anyway. Um, but there's other stuff. Actually not even eight,
six verses of it. Yeah, yeah, yeah, the highlights.
Yeah, but I mean the word antichrist doesn't even show up in any of that.
It's St. John who gives us that actual word.
Right, but not in the book of Revelation.
Not in the book of Revelation, right?
But in first John, which we're going to talk about last.
There we go.
So as usual with us, we're going to get to the only passages that use the term antichrist.
In our episode about the antichrist dead last.
Yep.
But you should know what you're getting into.
now when he listened to the show. Yeah. So we actually comparatively, we got to the topic,
at least broadly, relatively quickly. Pretty quickly. Yeah. So, yeah. So the other
the other uh, Lutestineman author who talks about the Antichrist, this final Antichrist figure is
St. John, as we just mentioned, in his apocalypse and in...
his first epistle. And so I felt the need not for speed, but
first top gun reference to separate this out a little bit. And to talk about
St. Paul first and then talk about St. John even though little bits of
St. John crept into St. Paul and little bits of St. Paul are now going to
creeping the St. John.
primarily because I was educated in the Western system.
No, there is predominant now in biblical scholarship
this idea, thanks to our 19th century German friends,
that there are theologies plural in the New Testament,
that different eye.
at minimum, different authors within the New Testament.
And of course, then you get into the whole issue
of modern scholarship, not thinking anybody wrote anything
and everything's written by different people.
And even this stuff we're attributing to say,
John was written by a bunch of different people, et cetera,
et cetera, et cetera.
But at the very bare minimum, any given author,
St. John has this theology and St. Mark has this other theology
say Paul.
has this other theology and they're separate
and they're not really commensurate.
And so there's piles of pre-suppositions
that go into this.
One of them being that, you know,
in the ancient world within nascent Christianity
like no one talked to each other,
but there were just all these completely
independent Christian communities
that did not communicate.
one wonders how they became Christian in the first place.
who were practicing potentially radically different things
that each other, like during the first century.
I know.
Not like later, not like second, century, third, century
where you have gnostic showing up
and this view is actually taken seriously by some people.
This, no, no, no.
This view is taken seriously by everyone.
Yeah, like it's the state.
I was trying to be a little restrained in my, in my every one.
But yeah, I mean it's like the standard view of-
of a lot of, you know, New Testament scholarship these conservative scholars.
Everyone, like I said, even I felt the need to kind of talk about St. Paul first
and then talk about St. John II, just because it's that ingrained, right?
But the presuppositions behind it, I've only begun to enumerate the stupid presuppositions
behind this.
I'll give some dumb examples.
Here's a dumb example.
St. Mark's gospel.
does not describe Jesus' birth.
Say, Mark's Gospel begins with Christ's baptism.
And so you will hear, otherwise intelligent people say,
well, whoever wrote Mark's Gospel,
because of course it can't be somebody named Mark.
Right.
As if St. Mark was famous for anything else
that you would put his name on this.
anyway you know all the father
go to this trouble to say, well, really this is Saint Peter's account, right? So if Saint
Mark is fictional, why didn't they just call it Saint Peter's Gospel? But anyway,
so whoever wrote Mark's Gospel must have had an adoptionist Christology.
Must have believed that Jesus became the Messiah and His baptism, not at His birth because He
doesn't describe His birth. Yeah. Okay. So why is this so stupid? Well, because
Yes, anything someone writes, right?
Anything I write, anything you write, anything anyone writes reflects the world of their
experiences, right?
Their views of things, their understandings of things of the world, the experiences they've
had are all reflected in what they write.
But they are not exhausted in each thing that they write.
Yeah.
Right?
Let's just call him St. Mark who wrote St. Mark's Gospel.
He did not write everything he believed thought did practice.
He did not write all of that into the 16 chapters of his gospel.
Yeah.
There was a thing he believed and knew and understood that he didn't write down in that one text.
Yeah. I mean, like you get this all the time, like on the internet, even just about like if I write an article, sometimes people like people like,
people like, well, you didn't cover this, you didn't cover this.
I'm like, well, no.
wasn't writing about that. Oh yeah, I have seen you accused publicly when you wrote an article and
just quoted scripture at it. They accused you of believing in Soluscripture. Right. If so,
then the fathers were believers in Soluscriptura. Right. So, right, because of course, you know,
that one text that you wrote, we can determine all of your views on everything.
And all of your under...
standing from that one tech, which is of course stupid. It's stupid. Okay. Um, next level
dumb. Rudolph Boltman. He's a 20th century jerk. Oh, man. Rudolph Boltman, uh, looks
at the gospel of Saint John. He's been proven wrong in almost everything he said about
Saint John, by the way. Right. I remember he said it was dothstick. I remember my one of my
one of my scripture professors in seminary like Boltman was like
like the devil in those classes.
Like whenever his name got mentioned,
it was, he was the composer.
Yeah, see, he's not the devil.
I know, no, no, but I mean, you know, he'd be deviled.
He was just, he was just working on a serious lack of data,
not thinking well and being very confident in conclusions
despite the lack of data and not thinking well.
But so he looked.
it's Saint John's Gospel and amongst other crazy things says, well look, hey,
Saint John's Gospel is the only Gospel where it doesn't give, tell or narrate Christ
initiating the Eucharist, right, saying this is my body, this is my, right, that's in the other
three Gospels, it's in 1 Corinthians, but it's not in Saint John's Gospel. And so he said,
Say, John's gospel was written by a community as if any text has ever been written by a
community and not one person in the community.
But anyway, it was written by a community that did not celebrate the Eucharist.
Now, is there any evidence whatsoever from any source that there was ever a Christian
church in the first century?
Well, he thought it was written in the second century also, which has also been proven
false.
In the second set, that did not practice the Eucharist in some way.
the no sticks had a Eucharist, right? Everybody had some kind of Eucharist, right? No, there's zero evidence.
The only evidence he has for it is that story is not in St. John's Gospel.
Amazing. And when someone said to him, hey, what about John 6?
Where he says, unless you eat my body, you drink my blood, right? You do not have a turtle life.
Real football said that can't be about the Eucharist.
Why? Because St. John's Gospel was written by a community that didn't practice the Eucharist.
And I assume he got paid to say things like this. This is what we call circular logic.
Yeah, right. Okay. So yeah. So the, but, but this same kind of thinking
to greater
lesser degrees is it's ubiquitous in biblical scholarship. You ubiquitous, even like conservatives,
if you try and bring in something from St. John to understand something and say Paul, they'll be like,
well, that way, wait, that's John. That's different. Right. And internally, internally, the New Testament
documents don't present themselves that way.
Internally, the New Testament documents where apostles refer to each other, where St. Peter
refers to St. Paul, where St. Paul refers to St. James and John and Peter.
They always express them as being an ultimate agreement.
Sometimes they describe sort of interesting confluence, but even that's rare.
That St. Paul and Galatians talking about a little set two he had with St. Peter and
that's about it.
That's all you got.
Right, there's an idea that there was some antipathy.
between St. Paul and St. James is fabricated.
It's not in the New Testament there is no source for it.
Sorry, Islamic Apologists.
So there is no basis for this internally
thinking that any of these writers were opposed to each other.
There is no logical reason to think
that someone could take one text written by an author
or two tax loo-
acts, right? Let's call it two texts, Luke and I, and say, okay, I could exhaustively determine
the religious way of life of the author of this from this text.
Right? We would never say that otherwise. You'd never say that about any text. I know
everything this person thinks about everything, how they live their life, the whole shot,
based on the fact that I read this one book they wrote. And that book they wrote is probably much
longer than any of the New Testament texts. So that doesn't make any sense.
Right? You add to this the way in which the New Testament canon came together. Right?
Which is not, as we've talked to the show before, that some guys somewhere sort of forced
these books altogether into a collection, even though they disagree with each other.
It's the opposite. The canon came together organically.
by 150
150, 81, 50
Every Christian church in every major city of the Roman Empire was using the four Gospels and only the four Gospels.
There was no Christian Emperor compelling them, no one was out there burning other books, nobody was forcing it, it happened organically.
And guess what? They could read. They weren't stupid, they saw that some of the details didn't match.
Get in there or where?
They still they still use them together, but they did not think
They did not think that that they were teaching different Christs
Yeah, no one knows no one was putting them against each other and like and I'll even say I think this is worth
pointing out like if you read saying nations of Antioch
Like his work is almost like a kind of
of
I'm an album of Joe and I and Pauline language.
Yeah.
Indicating that he, and what's interesting is he doesn't have a quote John directly, which strongly
suggests that he may not have access to his actual writings, but he just had him as his
teacher.
You know, but if you read his, if you read his letters, it's almost like it's John and
Paul speaking together with one voice, which is just kind of just goes to show that that's
That's how the church received them, you know, as two teachers.
is talking about the same Christ. And, you know, I'll use the lingo, right? The texts
ascribed to John, the Johanning literature emerged from Western Asia Minor, from churches
at St. Paul planted, as we mentioned earlier. Yeah, yeah. These are not two different geographical
millions. Yeah. Two different sets of communities. Sorry Rudolph. Right. Just as
happen. So what accounts for these sometimes differences or different ways of using words
or different terms being used like the term antichrist being used by St. John in one place
not in another and not by St. Paul. What we have to realize is that not just the text
of the New Testament, I've hammered on this with the text of the New Testament, but all
writing, everything that any human has ever written.
is occasional. It is written at a point in time for a purpose with an intended
readership. Right? When I write a grocery list, right, which I don't my wife does,
but were I to be the one to write the grocery list? It would be shorter, more boring,
and the food would not be nutritious. But also, right, I would be
writing it in a response to a certain need, I need food to eat for the next week.
And therefore, I would try to put together a list of food that should I eat that food over
the next week, I would be nourished, satisfied, what have you. I would list foods that were to my
taste and leave out ones that weren't. I would write it in a way, and Father Andrew could attest to
this because he has seen like show outlines I've written in a way that would probably
be intelligible only to me. Right? Like weird words and phrases that were evocative, but
that would remind me of something. Right? Because my intended audience is not someone else
to read my grocery list and understand it. It's just me. Right? So all that would be true
with my grocery list. All of that is also true of St. Paul's epistle to the Romans. You
He wrote it in his particular time with particular things happening in the world.
the Christian community in the city of Rome to answer certain questions and deal
with certain problems they were having. He had an intended audience, he used
language that he believed they would understand in their time and place. To
convey to them the things that he wanted to communicate to them. It's true of every
other text in the New Testament. Every other text in the New Testament. So, St. John
is writing
a different community in a different place at a different time,
dealing with different issues, then the issues that St. Paul was writing
to Thessalonica to address.
So they can refer to the same traditions, the same ideas,
the same teachings regarding the antichrist figure.
But because they have different audiences at different times
different times and different places, right? They can use different language.
and emphasize different parts and elements of that tradition in different ways of coming at that tradition
and they're not disagreeing with each other. They're not presenting two different theologies.
They're presenting the same thing, right? And so this is the extra step of interpretation
that's required in interpreting anything, any writing, right?
is the first step of interpretation is contextual.
Getting at as best we can, that original year, the original recipients, what they were
dealing with, how this addressed it.
And then there's this other step where we take it and we apply it for our purposes.
This is what you see the father is doing with Scripture.
They take something that St. Paul wrote to one community for a particular purpose, and
then say John Chrysostom looks at what St. Paul did, right?
and what he communicated to the community he was writing to
and St. John goes and he says the same thing, homiletics,
tries to convey the same thing, the same Christ, right?
Ultimately, to the people he's preaching to in Aniach
or in Constantinople, and does a fabulous job of it
because he's St. John Chrysostom, right?
But we can no more go and just
quote St. John, then we could just go and quote St. Paul.
When we interpret St. John and Christos, then we have to do the same thing.
We have to say, what is he conveying?
How is he conveying Christ, ultimately who Christ is, to the people he's preaching to?
And how can I communicate that same thing to the person I'm talking to in, you know,
Southern Louisiana in the 21st century?
And the language I use is probably going to be, it's not going to be Greek.
which I use is going to be different than St. John's and St. Paul's.
But if I'm doing it right, I'm not going to be contradicting them.
I'm not going to be doing something different.
And so this is how we have to understand these things.
So all of this is me taking a bunch of shots at modern biblical studies.
But also to say that St. John and St. Paul are not teaching something different.
different.
on this. Right? But they are writing in different circumstances, different genres even in the case of the book of Revelation.
And so they're focusing on and conveying different elements of the tradition that they're referring to and that they're sort of synthesizing in a Christian way and then teaching.
So, uh, okay.
Is that clear as mud, but it covers the ground.
So what is in those Joanine texts?
Yeah. So we're going to start with Revelation, which is everyone knows is simple and easy to understand.
Amen.
But so the figure associate, even though he's never called the Antichrist or the man of lawlessness for that matter,
the figure who's associated with the Antichrist and rightly so in the book of Revelation is the beast.
Okay, specifically the B-Stat of the C, in relation to 13.
But...
What St. John is doing there in his vision, right, there is a sort of, I mean, this is a vision
St. John receives, but again, St. John is a person who is steeped in Old Testament prophecy
and prophetic imagery.
So when he has his vision, God communicates through that vision with him using the imagery
of Old Testament prophecy that's familiar to him.
And so we have to take a look at the beasts in Daniel briefly before we get to the beast,
right, the beast of beasts, the super beast in Revelation 13.
Okay. And Daniel's beast, of course, he sees this succession of beasts in Daniel 7.
This is actually the story of the beast surrounds the story of the enthronement of the Son of Man
son of man that we've talked about a bunch before on the show.
So we're not going to get back into that here.
We'll talk about the beast part briefly.
And what you have, there's this succession of beasts
that are these sort of amalgamations of animal forms
that represent a succession of empires,
Babylon, Persia, Greece, and Rome.
And it's sort of parallel to the vision of the statue
that Daniel interprets for Nebuchadnezzar
with the statue made of the different metals.
Right, same kind of idea.
You could especially see some of this symbolism with Greece and the horns and Alexander.
Alexander on coins has Rams horns, which was a way of portraying him as divine.
I won't go into the other way he was portrayed as divine because he's a completely panicked
father-and-er.
You can look that up in other ways if you need to everybody.
someday, someday. Maybe I'll talk about that. Somebody, okay, so at the conference, we're going to have a live Q&A that's not, oh, no, that's going to be recorded. It'll be recorded.
Go to me at the conference and I'll tell you all about it. Maybe you could find me. Maybe you can hire the AT. Anyway.
So, but the core of what's going on in Daniels, that there are these just like with the statue
that gets destroyed by the rock, you know.
right without human hands, that the beasts are defeated at the Son of Man's enthronement.
Right. And interestingly in Daniel 7, even though they're defeated when the Son of Man is enthroned,
they're only finally sort of destroyed and punished after a time.
Hmm. So this part of Daniel 7 is actually also one of the key texts
related to the Messiah ruling in the midst of his
which we will be talking about in a future eschatology series episode about the
millennium. I have spoken, not next episode but soon.
A future. All of our eschatology episodes are in the future.
Yeah, ironically.
So, except this one. Well, parts one is in media race.
So, uh...
When we come to Revelation 13 and we see the beast out of the sea, we've talked about
before how this is associated with Leviathan and Bahemot or Bahimuth, the beast from the
land. But the beast out of the sea, you can see a sort of an amalgamation of all of Daniel's
beasts, right? That's why you get this super beast kind of imagery, right? You also have
the imagery of the beast as a king with blasphemous names.
right, and this beast with the kings, with the Bosos names has authority over every tribe
and people and language and nation that he achieved through conquest, right. And so,
for anyone living in St. John's time facing Roman persecution, this is ringing a lot of
bells, right? Like, St. John is not really secretive that he's talking about Rome, right?
Right. Right. Got the the the
Babylon who sits on seven hills like hello. Right, but even like the blasphemous names. Right,
you look at the official titles of Caesar, which include Lord Kerios,
Savior of the world, Son of God. Right, these are almost every title that's ascribed to Christ in
to the New Testament was a title of...
So, blasphemous names, but the blasphemous name thing really started with, all the way back with the Seljukids, who, you know, we're familiar with maybe Antiochus IV epiphanies, right? Who did the abomination of desolation?
But epiphanies there was that he was the manifestation of a God.
Right?
Yeah.
and savior, Sotere was another common title.
I think it was his father, might have been his grandfather,
who had Sotere, one of the Tommy's had Sotere.
This was a common thing, and Caesar had just kind of
balled all of those up and taken them all for himself,
from all of those previous rulers.
So clearly, St. John is talking about Rome,
but again, he's talking about more than just Rome.
Right. Rome is sort of a prime example.
of what he's talking about. Rome was the current, the contemporary example at the time, St. John
has this vision of what he's talking about. And in him presenting Rome as anti-Christ, we have
to realize that there were people like Josephus, the famous Jewish historian, Josephus at the end
of the day concluded that Rome was the Messiah. Which is amazing. Yes, for so many reasons.
Anyway.
that Rome was the savior of the world.
Yeah.
This is after the Jewish Revolts.
Wow.
Talk about a collaborator.
I know.
I mean, that's pretty much as collaborating as you get.
Right, right.
But so this is the antithesis of that, right?
No.
Right?
This is this is this is anti-Christ, right?
And so this is Rome as a world system,
but also Caesar as the embodiment of it, right?
in Pirator as the embodiment of it. And of course, then you get the number of the beast,
right? Insert jokes about apartment 665 being the neighbor of the beast, etc.
Right? And you know, this episode of ours is episode 66. I was like, well, it's too bad
we haven't done 600 more episodes. But we'll get there. You know what Meatloaf said, two out of
three aim back. There you go. Um so...
So folks may be familiar with if they dip their toes in the biblical studies stuff a little bit that the earliest manuscripts we have of Revelation, which are not that early by the way, but the earliest ones we have actually have 16 or 616,
And, you know, people get worked up about it because they like to find things to get worked
up about.
But what's going on?
One here is that this is what's called Gamatria.
This is using numbers to represent letters, right?
Which comes about as a reverse of what was normally done.
As we've talked about in the show before, normally, they didn't have numerals, so they use letters
to represent numbers, right?
And so this is the way of using those letter numbers to represent other letters.
It's a way of encoding something.
and the fact that he's at coding sub...
think St. John kind of telegraphs because he's like, let the reader understand, you know,
it is the number of a man.
Right.
Wink, right?
So it's kind of obvious to everyone anyone reading it that this is something encoded.
So St. Irenaeus and St. Hepatus say that this is encoded Taton or Titan or Typhon.
you
in both cases and for both figures, both of these fathers, this is clearly like trying to draw
it back to the Nephilim story, right? Because of course the Titans are taken to be, if we see the
story of the Titans as Pro-Devil propaganda, they're taken to be the angels who send, as being
the equivalent of like the watchers in the Book of Enoch.
And who takes it that way? We'll say Peter takes it that way.
Right? Say Peter talks about the angels imprisoned in Tartarus, which is the place where the Titans were imprisoned.
He's the only author who uses the word Tartarus in the New Testament.
So that's who the Titans were. Typhon is probably a little less well known.
Typhon is so after the imprisonment.
of the Titans that are in prison of the Titans by the Olympians.
Gaea, who's technically one of the, is sort of an ure Titan.
The Earth, Gaea gets mad.
And first she brings forth the Giants to attack,
get revenge for the Titans of the Olympians,
leading to the Greek Gigantomachy.
And then sort of her final step after the defeat of the Giants
is to bring forth Typhon,
Who is this giant monster beast?
an amalgamation of all these different animal forms that comes up out of the Mediterranean Sea
to kill Zeus to get revenge. Right? So either Typhon or Titan, we're connecting this back to
Greek versions of the Nephilim story. Right? And you can see how Typhon would connect to a beast out
out of the seat too. Right. And so we're associating in this case.
Roman Rome's king, right? Caesar with, you know, who presented himself as a god,
and I have these blasphemous names with the Nephilim, right? The Old Testament. So those fathers
are not wrong. That is an association that's happening here, right? But I think you could make a very
good case that the Gammatri is way more specific than that. And to me, the clincher for this is the
fact that this makes sense of both numbers. This works for 666.
6 and 616. Right. So the Greek form of the name for Nero Caesar, right? In Hebrew or
Aramaic is these are transliterated into English is N-R-O-N-Q-S-R. That's the
Standarting.
translation of the Hebrew consonants and the one long vowel, which is wow.
Neuroces are basically Neuropeiser. Yeah, but with a noon right in
Neuro. So it's Neurone. Right. That gives you the commentary on that is 666. If
you drop that extra noon so that it matches the Latin consonants in Hebrew and
there, man, you get six, one, six.
So that works for both. So the idea here is that St. John is not just using Rome as the contemporary
image for what he's talking about, but he's using a particular Caesar, Nero, the Caesar who killed
St. Peter and Paul and lots of other Christians is using him as again an emblem.
automatic
person, right?
Kane is an archetypal center, right?
Near on his sort of being used here as an archetypal, Near was being used in an archetypal
figure.
Now you might say, well, wait a minute, right?
According to St. Aaron As, St. John received his vision around 9596 AD, right?
Or 80, 95, 96.
was dead a long time.
before that. Right? You got off. But, right? Well, notice two things. Number one, St. John describes
the beast as having had a fatal wound that was healed. And at the time that St. John received
his vision, there was a widespread belief in tradition that Nero was not-
In fact, debt. He says he's not dead. Not dead yet. So that he had actually been grievously
wounded, but went into hiding in Asia Minor near where St. John received his vision supposedly
and that he was going to recoup and then come back and save the empire. Yeah. Because
the end of the first century.
like many other times in Roman history,
things weren't going so well.
It was good to think everything was collapsing.
Yeah, sort of the original Arthur story
and in that element of it,
the idea of going off the field and I'll be back.
And so there are Roman sources where you can read about this.
Right?
Around 80, 80, 88.
So not long before this vision,
Dio Chris Eston,
Chris Eston was a title that was given to St. John,
it was given to other people too.
The Eucharist.
the Stone is a pagan Roman.
But in his discourse, 21, he refers to this.
The Sibley and Oracles, four and five, refer to this.
Tacitus refers to this in histories to eight.
Sutonius refers to this in section 57, right?
So this is a tested, this is a belief.
And it's only attested by this, but historically,
there were phony neurons who showed up
and tried to claim the imperial throne
Hit it
Then, Roeb
...
in this period and thereafter. People showed up claiming to be Nero, coming back.
And this tradition was so pervasive and so entrenched in Roman thought that it was still around in
St. Augustine's day. St. Augustine in the city of God 2019-3 says that as the Western Empire was
collapsing at the big in the early fifth century. There were a lot of
barely converted pagans who said, oh Christianity was a mistake. That's why the Western Empire is falling and
Nero is going to come back and rescue us and make the Empire pagan again and turn all this around
right, so
again in the same way that
Julian the Apostate ended up being sort of
the image or the icon or the emblematic figure of the Antichrist for a lot of the fathers.
In late antiquity, Nero here is presented by St. John and becomes for generations of Christians
thereafter, especially in the West, the image of the Antichrist in the same kind of way.
And again, the way St. John describes it, and the way these people up to St. Augustine
describe it is, Nero is going to reappear. Right, and you could compare that to the
language St. Paul uses in 2 Thessalonians 2 where both Christ appears, right, what we would
call a second Advent, second coming, and the man of lawlessness appears, right, and Nero
is going to reappear, right? And so this idea that the anti-Christ is going to be someone
who does a counterfeit resurrection, right? He's going to be this God-king-fear who does
a fake, a phony resurrection.
sort of a parody of Christ's actual resurrection, right?
You can see how that becomes an archetypal image.
But of course, say John is not saying,
oh, Nero's the final antichrist,
and then that, you know, that's it.
Either this is gonna happen soon,
or he's gonna come back as the antichrist
at some point in the future.
He's not identifying him as the final antichrist.
And how do we know that?
Well, we know that because of how St. John talks
about.
the the Antichrist in first John where he actually uses the word.
Yeah. Yep. Yep. And what he says, there's very consonant with what St. Paul talks about with
the mystery of lawlessness, right, that is already at work in the world, right, and already impinging.
So
First John 2, 18 is kind of the famous one.
Yeah, exactly.
It's real brief.
Children, it is the last hour.
And as you have heard that anti-Christ is coming,
so now many anti-Christ have come.
Therefore, we know that it is the last hour.
Right.
And so,
right, you have heard.
Yeah, it's that right.
And anti-Christ is coming.
Single, there's going to be this singular figure.
Already there's a bunch of them.
So it's not just one figure.
There is an ultimate figure in the future.
But there are already figures, right?
And how do those figures work?
First John 4 verse 3.
He talks about the
Spirit of Antichrist.
Yeah, so every spirit that does not confess Jesus is not from God.
This is the Spirit of the Antichrist which you heard was coming and now is in the world
already.
Yes.
Right?
So you've heard the Antichrist is coming.
The Spirit of Antichrist is already active in the world and is motivating these people,
right?
Making them, them Antichrists, right?
And so this spirit of Antichrist, the miss-
of lawlessness, right? These are not different concepts, right? These are the same kind of ideas.
And in fact, to put a finer point on it, Saint Paul refers to in second Thessalonians,
St. Petersburg's 9th, the energies of Satan. Yeah. Which gets translated like,
ESP has activity of Satan, but I mean that's the same thing. That's energy. Yeah. Yeah.
that the Antichrist, when St. Paul uses it in second Thessalonians,
too, he's talking about the Antichrist working counterfeit signs and miracles
through the energies of Satan, the energy, yeah.
Right?
The idea being there actually the works of the devil.
And he is doing them.
He is bringing them into reality in the world.
He is cooperating with Satan.
Right, rather than cooperating with
And this is the perspective that St. John has in 1 John.
In 1 John 3 verses 8 through 12, from Cain on, uses Cain as the archetypal center.
From Cain on, these anti-Christ figures, they do the works of the devil in the world.
And Christ comes to destroy those works.
Right. Christ comes to destroy those works.
So.
A concept we have to understand here in terms of the relationship between Christ and the
Antichrist, in terms of Antichrist and Antichrist figures in the scriptures and in history,
is the idea of negative typology.
And negative typology is really a kind of demonic parody, ultimately.
So, uh...
positive typology, right? It would be typology the way we probably normally think about it.
Yeah, right. There's some aspect of someone or someone's life in the scriptures or in history with
the saints that is that points toward or exemplifies or images, some element of the person of Christ
or the work of Christ.
Yeah, like an obvious excuse.
example would be Joseph, you know, the son of Jacob as a type of Christ, you know, all
the things he goes through and the things he does and so forth, that would be an obvious
example of that kind of positive typology.
Right.
Or the sign of Jonah, right.
Yeah.
Three days.
Right.
This is the only thing about it.
And this is, this is positive but not full.
Right.
Meaning, you know, we can point to this in Jonah without saying, okay, well, Jonah was perfect.
Right part of-
the typology is that in Christ we find the fullness of that, right? Or with Joseph, in Christ
we find the fullness of that, right? There's also negative typology where elements of Christ,
of the person of Christ, or of Christ's work are inverted or bent or twisted, right? And so
So I put forward in this warped way.
or even an inverted, a flipped over way.
Yeah. And I mean, and an anti-Christ, like, the seems obvious to point out, but worth saying,
an anti-Christ is a type of Christ. Otherwise, he wouldn't be an anti-Christ. He would be just
a bad person or whatever, you know. Right. Right. He was a type of Christ in this negative way.
right, right? And we kind of saw this idea that St. Paul was
with in second Thessalonians 2, where Christ humbles himself and is exalted, whereas the
anti-Christ exalts himself and is destroyed. That's an inversion. It's the opposite.
By looking at that opposite, you can see something about the true, the real. You can see
something about Christ by seeing the inverse.
right because Christ is the opposite.
Right? And right, you can see this even, here's an example of negative typology.
From St. Paul, we referred to Romans 5 earlier, right, where he makes this comparison between Adam and Christ.
Right? And he said where Adam is disobedient and Christ is obedient. Right? That's negative typology.
opposite right Adam transgressed Christ is not right Adam brings death Christ
brings life right so that's negative typology but that negative typology doesn't
mean that Adam's like an evil person yeah or it right like he's not so you can
keep if you have an icon of just Adam, right, you can you can keep that. Right. The
that he in this sense served as a negative type of Christ, or you could even say a type of antichrist.
Right? Does not mean that he is not ultimately, he did not ultimately as a person
become a saint. Right? It's what it's the place that he's serving narratively. Right. Yeah. But the opposite
it is also true. The opposite is also true that someone
serving as there being some positive typology between a person in Christ does not make them a
saying. Yeah, right. And I mean, and there's there's even positive typology about animals and
objects that is related to Christ. Right. Yeah. Right. So for example, right, when we when we hear
song and read the interpretation that the donkey that Christ rode.
on at the triumphal entry was a type and image of the Gentile Church. Right? We're not going to make
icons and dedicate churches to St. Donkey because Donkey is a type of the church. Right? That's a
ridiculous example. Right? But this applies to humans too. One could, for example, Saul, Old Testament
So, now...
Saul who becomes Saint Paul, Old Testament Saul. I've never seen an icon of him, have you?
No. I had for really good reason, right? He ends his life demon possessed.
Yeah.
Committing suicide. Yeah. Okay. But he was the king of Israel.
One could make positive typology between him and Christ at certain points in his life and
and certain stories about his life.
Fuzz.
the whole thing about going and finding his father's donkey's and so. Right?
There so, right? Someone can at times of places be an image of Christ and even, and even,
dare I say it, can even be a Christian. Right? And unfortunately, apostatized to bring this
back full circle. Right? So, typology and the person's salvation or the person's
relationship as person with God.
are not one to one. So you can have a saint like Adam where there's a negative typology,
a negative comparison between him and Christ in certain ways, but he's still a saint,
ends up being a saint, and you can have other figures who I won't name because there's been
enough of that on the internet. That's who in some ways might have served as a positive type of
price. I mean, it's a Saul, I guess we'll do that one. But who do not end up being
themselves, even though at times in certain elements of their story, may have this positive
typology related to Christ. But this is at the core of something we've talked about,
we talked about early on in the show actually, of seeing myth and religious practice outside
of Ancient Israel outside of Second Temple Judaism outside of Christianity.
as Pro-Devil propaganda, right?
That these are not just random unrelated stories
that are piffles and can be dismissed, right, as silly
fables, but nor are they the truth, right,
that we have within that tradition throughout history
that I just described, right?
feature inversions.
of the truth, distortions of the truth,
bending of the truth.
And this is how when you take a nuanced view of how the father's
read Homer or Plato or whomever.
This is what you actually see.
They're saying this emerges from the actual world,
which includes the spiritual world.
And is a description of it.
and it's a description of
events in it, but it's one that's warped, it's one that sometimes outright inverted,
flipped 180 degrees, flipped in like photo negative, but even from those images, if you understand
them and how to work with them, you can show how they represent and connect back to and
can help illuminate the truth.
And so they're neither discarded nor embraced.
Right.
Nor just sort of cherry picked, well here are the nice parts and we'll put out the expirgated
bold-larized version without all the naughty bits and that'll be the Christian version.
Right.
But a much more nuanced way of interacting, right, with it.
Yeah.
Yeah, so to some of my final thoughts.
You know, I was raised as a conservative evangelical Protestant, and especially in the period of the 1970s and 80s and 90s.
That means a lot of dispensationalism. You know, I really can't get away from it.
We don't need to go into exactly what
dispensationalism is.
I mean, you can look it up on the interwebs.
But a major piece of it is this idea that
You know, the end of the world is at hand.
And I remember books like Late Great Planet Earth
from Howl Lindsay in the 70s.
And I think he didn't, didn't that book predict
that the end of the world would be like 1988?
I think that's what it was.
It did not end in 1988.
But I mean, there's been a millionaire in Fervor like this
in many periods in history.
you know, one in the 19th century that ended up being...
called the Great Disappointment by the Millerites.
And one of the things that you often see happen
when people have Millenarian fervor,
like the sense that the world is ending.
And I think a lot of people these days do have the sense.
I mean, there's all kinds of just nutty stuff happening
and not just nutty stuff.
There's a lot of dangerous violent stuff happening, right?
And a lot of folks, they put all these things together
say this is it, this is it.
You know, and they may even attempt to identify particular figures as being the Antichrist.
You know, the signs are all lining up, you know, and all this kind of thing.
I think my favorite millennialist, I've seen on the, or millennial, I've seen on the interwebs
lately as a guy who calls himself the third eagle of the apocalypse.
His music is really catchy.
And with this idea that the world is ending,
a lot of times people get the sense that the rules change as a result.
I mean, if you think that the world is ending, it's true.
You tend to lose some of your inhibitions.
You tend to...
Everything's hyped up.
You know, your feelings are stronger about things.
You become more fervent or more depressed or whatever.
there.
Um.
And I mean, this works both on the macro level where you think the world is ending, and
also just the level where your world is ending.
Like, if your life is falling apart, there's this sense that the rules don't really apply
or that the rules change.
You know, like, look, we're all about to lose everything.
So therefore we've got to really focus on X, Y and Z and the normal restraints, you know,
don't apply.
I've even seen this to our shame within some Orthodox circles these days, right?
There's this idea out there.
We live in the time of Antichrist, and so therefore we don't have to be obedient to bishops.
So here's the thing about all that.
That is just utterly ignorant of Scripture.
As we saw what St. John said, you know, anti-cr...
have come, spirit of anti-Christ is at work in the world.
And he wrote this almost 2,000 years ago, right?
And even this idea that's out there,
you know, we don't really have to be obedient to bishops
because the time of the anti-Christ is here.
Like I read one person saying this,
when someone, for instance, was mentioning
the ecclesiology of synagmatia, sovantiac,
which he talks very clearly about obedience to bishops.
I mean, there's one point where even says, you know,
If someone is worked.
apart from the bishop, he worships the devil. Like it's really strong language.
And they'll say, well, Ignatian ecclesiology doesn't really apply anymore because we're in the
time of Antichrist. But St. Ignatius was a disciple of the Apostle John who said those things about
Antichrists already coming and the spirit of Antichrist already in the world. So in other words,
talked about his ecclesiology during a time
that his own teacher said was a time of Antichrist.
So it wasn't like, well, everything is great.
And Christians are free and everything.
It was a really bad time for Christianity.
Nations himself wrote this as he was on his way to be martyred.
But even aside from just this question of
whether we should obey,
ships are not in the time of anti-crest.
Obviously, the general answer to that is yes.
If a bishop tells you to do something sinful, you don't do it.
That's always been true.
But they don't lose all their authority because it's a time of Antichrist because here's
a thing.
A Piscopal authority is set up within the time of Antichrist, which has been the case
for 2000 years now.
But the broader issue of, you know, should I behave differently because this is the time
of Antichrist?
The answer is no.
Or yes, but here's what way yes.
If we really understand what it means that we're in the time of Antichrist, understanding
that that's been the case for 2000 years now, or more depending on how you, you know,
whether you're applying it even to Old Testament stuff, which clearly is a thing, then that
being at work in the world, the way that you fight back against that is by the life of
faithfulness by the life of prayer and worship and kindness and love and arms.
giving and fasting and all of these things that we know are the weapons of the spiritual
war. Right? Sometimes people feel like a time of anti-Christ means it's time to get crazy.
It's time to be extreme, a time to be nasty to other people. Right? You know, because when
of a feeling that the world is ending, people can get very agitated. But the
call is the same. You know, even if like the final anti-Christ is alive in the world today
and it work in the world today and like this is the truly the last generation, the call to
Christians is the same as it was when the New Testament was written. It's the same. It has
not changed. There is no call like different rules apply now or the old rules don't apply anymore.
That is not true. That is not true. The called
faithfulness is the same. We still have to love. We still have to give arms. We still have to be
faithful and prayer and worship fasting and all these things like this is still the norm. It's been
the norm. I think, you know, one of the things that we talked about was the idea that the
liturgy in a sense holds back the end of the world. That's that really summarizes a lot of what I'm
I'm trying to say here is that that what
is the task, it's to enter into worship,
it's to enter, and then all the things that flow from worship.
And realize that our task as a church
is to try to rescue our fellow humans
to bring them into the church.
Not to say, well, it's the time of Antichrist,
so you're all my enemies, so it's okay for me to blast you
and be nasty to you and not care about the salvation
of your soul, or think that being nasty
is caring about the salvation of someone's soul.
it's not, you know.
If we're going to be like the saints, then we need to be like the saints.
We need to behave the way that they behaved.
And don't just pick out the parts that appeal to us.
Like, oh, I love it when they're polemical.
No, that's actually, they only entered into that when they really felt that they needed to,
and they were defending actual undermining of the body of the church.
The rules are still the same.
The life of...
faithfulness is still the same because it was formulated in the time of Antichrist.
So yeah, we're in the time of Antichrist. I'm not saying it's not going to end tomorrow.
The world's not going to end tomorrow. I don't know. It might, but the rules today are
still the same as they were 2000 years ago. And if the world doesn't end tomorrow,
that's to be the same next week, it's still the same. So we don't need to get agitated,
Christ said
you
good cheer, thrive overcome the world. That's peace. That's that's joy. And Christians should
be known for their peace, their joy, their genuine love for each other, for other people.
So rules are the same. Keep living the right way, become more faithful. Father, your final
thoughts.
Yeah, so I never had to dispense with dispensationalism, because I knew I was not blinded.
And I wasn't surrounded by a lot of people playing pin the tail on the Antichrist, though
I was aware of it right out there in evangelical culture.
For the record, all those people who have picked Antichrist throughout history, almost
All of them were right.
Yeah, sure. Not about which one was the final one, but most of the people they picked,
you know, Hitler, Stalin, Lenin, Napoleon, Ronald Wilson Reagan, who had six letters
in each of his three names. Think about it. But most of them, most of them were actually
right. And this is because, right as St. Paul said, the
of lawlessness as St. John said, the mystery, or the spirit of Antichrist is out there in the world and is active.
And unfortunately, the reaction most of us take to this, at least in the contemporary period, at least in the United States, which is where I happen to live.
So I can only speak from my own experience.
is not to stand.
not to stand as a garrison or a bulwark in any sense, but to hunker down to go and hide.
Past generations of Christians have interacted with the culture that was full of
sin and corruption brought about by the same spirit of antichrist by producing works of beauty,
Poetry
arts, works of fiction and nonfiction learning by interacting critically with their culture
and society, exposing falsehoods, teaching and promoting the truth in ways that have transformed
cultures in various places.
And the closest we can get, especially in the US, is fighting a lame culture.
war, which is, hey, let's have a boycott so that this cheap Belgian beer stops putting gay
people in their ads and goes back to women in bikinis. Christian values, right? That's
our idea of oh yeah, we're gonna we're gonna fix the culture. We need the dog on the boogie board
again in the beer commercial. Then everything will be great. Or maybe you know big horses and a
a big American.
flag. We think we're you know, fighting some kind of culture war when we buy our chicken sandwich
at one restaurant rather than another. And it's frankly pathetic. We've surrendered.
We've given up on teaching or putting out or producing anything of value or anything of worth
uh...
anyone but maybe our own communities.
And that's not what our forebears in the faith did,
even in much more hostile environments.
When faced with a paganism that had dominated the world,
the worship of demons, sexual morality,
penoracity as a cultural institution in the Roman Empire.
Right, Christians went and took those pagans own works.
reinterpreted them and showed them the lies taught them the truth, right?
Stood for what was true and ended up changing that world. They didn't hunker
down. They didn't hide. And so I think as Father Andrew said, we are now as we
we have in every other age, been living in the spirit of Antichrist.
for the mystery of lawlessness is at work in the world.
But we've been called to be this garrison.
We've been called to stand in a fight to ward that off,
not to ward that off from our small insular community,
not to cover our kids eyes so they don't see it,
toward it off from the world,
the earth, the world.
That's what we're called to do.
do. And we saw tonight.
from Scripture what the weapons of our warfare are, their worship, their prayer,
their kindness in the world, but they're also teaching. They're also interacting
with things critically and publicly, right? And seriously, seriously, not just
just again picking sides in the dumb dumb culture war.
But seriously interact.
right and doing this in public with real actual people in the world who we can meet and talk to and
break bread with because you're not you as a person are not called to do this for the whole world.
We as a church spread throughout the world are called to do this for the whole world.
You're called to do this in your world, your corner of it.
Those people who you can see, not on the internet, not on social media, where you virtue
to sing the lower part.
or whatever, the actual humans who are available to you to sit down and break bread with,
to have a discussion with, to talk about the ideas they've imbibed from the world around them.
Maybe where some of those are wrong, maybe where some of them are 180 degrees wrong,
inverted from the truth. Maybe where some of them are just a little bent and we can straighten them out.
and bring them to come to know Christ.
Because as beleaguered, and this is frankly kind of pathetic too, American Christians thinking they're so beleaguered and persecuted compared to our brothers and sisters in other parts of the world.
But as beleaguers, you may feel we don't actually want the end to come.
I still need time to repent.
more of it that I'll probably get because I would
I need to live to be 180, but to even make a good start.
But we need more time to repent.
There are people out there who are still lost,
who need to come to know Christ.
And so I don't want the end to come yet.
But to do that, we're gonna have to stand in the midst,
not off in a corner, not hiding.
And we're gonna have to intervene.
and we're gonna have to take a stand.
And we're going to have to do the messy business of getting to know our fellow human beings
in the little world that God has placed us in to bring it to Him in Christ.
Those are my thoughts.
Amen.
Well, that's our show for tonight.
Thank you for listening everyone.
If you didn't get through to us live, we'd still love to hear from you.
You can email us at Lord of Spirits at Ancient Faith.com.
can send us a message or a Facebook.
or you can leave us a voicemail at SpeakPipe.com slash Lord of Spirits.
And join us for our live broadcast of the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 PM Eastern 4 PM Pacific
where we won't take no prisoners and won't spare no lives.
And if you are on Facebook, you can follow our page, you can join our discussion group,
leave reviews and ratings in the appropriate places. Most importantly, share this show with a friend
whom you know is going to benefit from it.
And finally, be sure to go to ancientfaith.com stroke support and help make sure we and lots
of other AFR podcasters stay on the air because nobody's putting up a fight.
Thank you, good night. God bless you, and I feel fine.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and riches
and with
and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.
Glory to God. This is the weekly podcast of Father Stephen Freeman from St. Ann
Orthodox Church in Oak Ridge, Tennessee and the author of the popular Glory to God for
all things block site. Here is Father Stephen.
Over the past couple of months and these podcasts I've been speaking about the difference
between what I call a...
one story universe and a two story universe.
It's simply language to speak about a difference
between believing in a God who is everywhere present and filling all things
that is present here with us, or having a religion in which
God and spiritual things have been relegated to some second story
part of the universe where they seem
at such a remove from us that they're not part of our everyday life.
So it's really a distinction between a world divided between sacred and secular,
or a world in which things are united, and which we live in the midst of holy things.
The comments that I've had from readers or from listeners
have told me that I've been writing and speaking about a topic that touches the hearts of many.
Perhaps the most poignant responses I've had have been those who have heard descriptions of
of the one story world.
entails of monastics in which language is clearly simple.
Amongst speak of God, they speak of the saints, they speak of miracles, visions, healings, etc.,
and precisely the same language they used to describe beings and sand, the sunrise, and everything else,
and their day-to-day existence. A miracle is as much a part of their day as the soup that sits before them.
The responses that I've had to such normalcy and
integration of the spiritual life have occasionally been of the sword I would expect.
Sponsors that say, this is wonderful. I would like to believe like that, but I find it so
hard. Perhaps the greatest journey many of us have to make in this modern age is the
journey from the corroded faith of modernity itself towards a faith worth believing.
have made a journey to the Orthodox Church because they...
sense that here such a faith can be found. Some have made that journey, though they have
not personally found such faith as yet. They are simply not willing to stay where they
have been, and listen either to the vapid emptiness of modern liberal Christianity or the
emotion-filled delusions of Pentecostalism, and much of modern-day Evangelicalism. And
thus they have made the difficult journey to Orthodoxy, waiting for the arrival of a
one story faith. A time when the
words they say and hear will become the words of their heart without question, without
second guessing. And this is a very difficult journey indeed. Part of this is simply the
plight of modern man. Modern man lives in a world in which faith has been largely removed,
faith has become a function of the second story. We may speak of things that have been relegated
to that realm and believe in them much like we
I can't remember what those are.
That the things on the second story are true, we believe.
Indeed, the doctrine about the things that have been relegated to that place are believed very vehemently by some.
For the doctrines are almost the sole intellectual content that we can access.
We cannot access the angels or God or the resurrection.
Instead, there are a set of rational principles derived from Scripture, perhaps even the fathers.
even the fathers and these we make.
access and believe and argue. But this is still not a faith worth believing.
Recently in my little town we endured a devastating tragedy. A young middle school girl, well
known to many in our town, we only have 25,000 here, was struck by a school bus on the
way home from school and died as a result of the accident. The pain engendered by such
event is beyond description. People's reactions.
are much as I would have expected. Even my own grief, at the time and news of the accident,
was palpable. But such a death simply moved to the second story.